<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Duell-ease A worde with. valiant spiritts shewing the abuse of duells, that valour, refuseth challenges and priuate combates. sett foorth by G.F. a defendour of Christian valoure.</title>
            <author>G. F., defendour of Christian valoure.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10637</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101807</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837610</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837610</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177091</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177091)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 789:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Duell-ease A worde with. valiant spiritts shewing the abuse of duells, that valour, refuseth challenges and priuate combates. sett foorth by G.F. a defendour of Christian valoure.</title>
                  <author>G. F., defendour of Christian valoure.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Ann Griffin London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The title page is engraved.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dueling --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177091:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177091:1"/>
            <p>True <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aloure</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Challenge.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aliantly refuſed Cowardly accepted</p>
            <p>I accepted the Challenge.</p>
            <p>Suffer.</p>
            <p>fight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who ſtandes not in his Li<hi rend="sup">•</hi>, Will Chooſe the right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I feele him not</p>
            <p>I better him.</p>
            <p>DVELL-EASE <hi>A WORDE WITH</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aliant Spiritts <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the abuſe of Duells, that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alour, refuſeth Challenges and</hi> Priuate Combates.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quicunque effuderit humanu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sanguine fundetur ſanguis eius.</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Who ſoe Sheddeth mans blood by man ſhall his blood be Shedd.</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>ſett foorth by G. F. a Defendour of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aloure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I reuenge.</p>
            <p>I Challenge</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Ann Griffin <hi>London.</hi> 1635.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nec enim Lex iustior <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lla. Quam necis artifices arte perire ſua Nor is ther Lawe more right<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then that Who drawes his brothers blood Shall Spill his owne by fight.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177091:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177091:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT AND POVVERFVLL PRINCE CHARLES, by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France, Ireland, Cyprus, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD hath ſtored your Maieſty with ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent wiſdome, as by it he ruleth more then your own kingdomes. You are his Eye for Europe, and at your ſacred girdle, Heaven hangs the Storehouſe-keyes of Chriſtian blood.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177091:3"/>
            <p> VVee may well ſay it; Since in this age of blood, none hath grieved more to ſpill it then your Maieſty, none laboured ſo much to ſpare it. You have weakned its ſwelling ſtreames, to the anger of puiſſant Princes.</p>
            <p>Had your Armies troden the bankes of <hi>Danow;</hi> Nations well know, what bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy floods you had encreaſed; Your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure Star hath led you a more milken way, rather to lead Chriſtian orbes quiet, then to haſten them to the wrenching of their owne ſinewes, ſatisfied in your ſelfe that thoſe who beſt uſe the Olive, will ſooneſt weare the Laurell.</p>
            <p>Wee have lived to ſee (but ô, teares ſhould have curtained our eyes) the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt inundation of blood that ever flowed from Chriſtian vaines, and that by ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tides. Great Kings have kept open the ſluces, whom in reſpects moſt proper to their boaſts of better Religion, it would better become to dry up thoſe ruddy
<pb facs="tcp:177091:3"/> ſprings, were it with the loſſe of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and fortunes. Say Chriſtian drums muſt needs beat, and bullets fly ſometimes to ſpend of their owne firy ſpirits, yet may they not finde out a fitter Enemy in <hi>Aſia,</hi> or frame one out of <hi>Africa?</hi> Heaven hath onely enlightened your Maieſty to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre deluges of homicides, wallowing in baptized bloud. Your reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll beames of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety moſt adviſedly reflected, that all quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels are not to bee decided by the ſword, nor every difference to make its full point at Tyburne. More, even in Kings, deſires, although iuſt, muſt not alwayes be obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, all cannot be had, many but at ſeaſons, and of thoſe which may be had, ſome ought to ſuffer a barre, but ſuch as ſhall bee war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with ages of happines. Not upon a croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>I will have,</hi> are bowels to be drawne out by the Hangman, or lims ſuddenly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by Armies; humane blood is a liquor not to be ſtirred without much warines; if wrongs draw it, it guſheth not out without
<pb facs="tcp:177091:4"/> crying to Heaven. <hi>Sanguis clamat de</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> 
               <hi>terra.</hi> The greateſt wit, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing a moſt valorous Prince ſaith, <hi>Parce effundere ſanguinem humanum.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ariſt. ad Alex.</note> Draw not the bloud of men by rivers, but by drops. What Art offered to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> your Maieſtie holdeth by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; whereby our <hi>Albania,</hi> better clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth now her name from the candorous ſplendour of your Royall Scepter then from her native Rocks. This your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt wary diſpoſition to prevent a waſte of men, wingeth my hopes flying to your Maieſties feete with theſe few leaves, which cover or diſcover (as your Maieſties bright ſhining eye ſhall open, or cloſe them) ſome few Antidotes to prevent and cure a fiery diſtemper, a Conſumption, or waſte of blood fatall to the noble bowels of your kingdome. Theſe times have begotten this idle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe in the brave ones, and they will owne it; that who is ſtained by any abuſe is bound in honour to ſcoure it by a
<pb facs="tcp:177091:4"/> challenge, and hee from whom the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake firſt ſlipt, muſt preſently be drawne to <hi>Calis ſands:</hi> whence if the one be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to a grave, the other walketh home with honour.</p>
            <p>Your radiant wiſdome to the high glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your Diadem enlightneth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifieth this mervailouſly miſtaken way. May a dueller raiſe honour, becauſe death ſtumbled upon the better man? No, it is not ever the lot of the Valiant or Innocent, to be death-free in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats, there are confuſed uncertainties: death is not alwayes borne by ſtrong armes, nor doth the mightineſſe of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood alwayes cite it: ſometimes a ſand under foot, a Moate in the Eye, a very ſilly misfortune brings it. But alas, this is a diſeaſe of cradle-courage: duellers, take them at any action of able men, and wee ſhall finde honour, and them of very ſmall acquaintance: yet forſooth they become honour-ſicke; for they deeme their honour muſt needes dye, unleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:177091:5"/> they drinke the blood of the braveſt.</p>
            <p>VVill Kings ſuffer them ſo pretious a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Niceph. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>hiſt Eccl. cap.</hi> 33. <hi>Bar. to.</hi> 3. <hi>Annal. ad an. Dom.</hi> 324.</note> potion? it is phyſicke too chargeable for a Kingdome. Great <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was but once allowed humane blood to cure his direfull diſeaſe, he thought it too deare for a <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and muſt meane duellers dayly to cure a diſtemper meerely in fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, bee permitted bloud, not of Infants, but of men? yea the ſtouteſt; for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to the meaner man an abuſe is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and to the better a Challenge; for by the better ſpirit, as readieſt to ſpend its mettall, the affront is offered, and by the baſer creature, a Challenge is thruſt on, as not able to creepe into Honour, but by the caſualty of a combat, where a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Coward is often Victor againſt a <hi>Hector.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this meanes is a way oft-times <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am</hi> 11. <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               </note> found to draw bloud out of the breaſts of your Maieſties beſt ſervants, and day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there are loſt brave ſubjects; which moved your Father of happy memory
<pb facs="tcp:177091:5"/> our dread Soveraigne Lord King <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ames,</hi> to thunder out by his Proclamations &amp; Edicts, ſevere puniſhments againſt all hatchers of Challenges, and putters on of ſuch counterfeit manhood.</p>
            <p>Wee hope your Maieſty will renew and endow them with a double vigour: penalties may bee put up upon ſuch as provoke duels, and a way layed open to an eaſie redreſſe of wrongs by whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver offered: So ſhall you become an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and we will ſay with <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, excubat Principis cura pro ſalute ſingulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Seneca de bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit vitae.</note> 
               <hi>omnium domos tua diligentia defendit, omnium delitias tua induſtria;</hi> your Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care aſſureth all men ſafety, freeing your faire dominions from the canker of Duelliſme, and fond Mothers ſhall owe unto you their darlings. Why may not Lawes cure loſſes of honour, as well as of life and fortunes? Let him keep his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell whom wrongs privately pinch, and they are cured; if abuſes further vent into an open noyſe, the Marſhals court may
<pb facs="tcp:177091:6"/> arraigne them; when the matter is ſcarce perceptible: it is much, ſo ſmall a weapon ſhould hurt one, and ſuch a perſon is too delicate, tender, and unfit to live among men that muſt briſtle: but if there be left a ſcarre, a blemiſh to be ſeene; your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty may gratiouſly provide for a faire ſatisfaction, and when wrongs be ſuch as dare not produce, but muſt hide their cauſe, there is no right owing them, as no light to darkeneſſe.</p>
            <p>Here I lay downe my pen, and deities; being to bee adored at a diſtance. From my chamber in the Temple, I kiſſe your Maieſties Royall feet, and with all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to your Crowne and Perſon; for which I am ready cheerefully to pawne the life of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull and moſt humble ſubiect. <hi>G. F.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:177091:6"/>
            <head>Preface.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Gentle Reader.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom the preſſe I come to</hi> Paules, <hi>to be gazed on by many: ſome will read and gueſſe at my good meaning, that it was not ſo much to keepe ſteele out of ſight, as to keepe manhood in poſſeſsion: and that my leaves of Paper are not for cowards to ſhelter themſelves under. I doe not aime to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe true valour, by branding it with ignominy: I guild not the droſſe of mankinde with glorious excuſes: the brave-worded faint-hearts with warranties of their effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate weakeneſſe. I rather doe honour unto manlike cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and wiſh it long life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I truely apprehend valour a pretious Iewell; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to bee handled diſreſpectfully: a principall orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a well ordered common weale, therefore not to be abuſed by every horſe-groome, not to be trampled in every taverne, nor to wayt upon every fond lover: with freedome may I ſpeake it; valour is not to be hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon meane enterpriſes, but to bee laid up for dearer times: by it Kings doe hold their ſcepters, without it E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
<pb facs="tcp:177091:7"/> will fall out of credit, and the world ſhall not dare to ſhew a good liking to honeſty: men muſt keepe courage to looke vice in the face; to make it to heare its owne name. And in this reſpect there is great overſight in the havocke of valorous ſpirits, which dayly the power of vulgar opinion maketh periſh in Duells.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet I doe not generally denounce an exile to all Duels, from al countreyes, from all occaſions; ſometimes they have their lawfulnes; the unadviſed are inſufferable, and ſuch I deſire to ſuppreſſe: the too too much levity in falling into wrath, turneth the merit of courage into a meere ſhaddow, which ever followeth, but ſuch as wander out of the light of reaſon, miſled by ſtrong paſsion: for certainly when the cauſes of quarrells are no bigger than little ſands, they lye onely on the eye of ſuch, as are over flowne with an Ocean of Anger.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Dueller.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>YOu will ſay I deale with brave Duellers, too too diſcourteouſly: favour me, it is your Vice I kicke at; I both honour and extoll your valour. Bee not offended, if I ſay Duels be bad, that they are acts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, unluckie, that the combater breedeth moſt miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe to himſelfe when he is victor, when he kils his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary: I doe but tell you what the nature of Duelliſme is. You will needs notwithſtanding make a challenge, you will goe to the field, when you rage: but underſtand, you goe out of your way, I ſhew it you, you are in the darke, in a paſsion; what harme doe I unto you, if I light you with a</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177091:7"/> 
                  <hi>candle? Stout</hi> Pericles, <hi>the mirrour of</hi> Athens <hi>and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſ. hom.</hi> 24 <hi>de legendis libris Gentilium.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>yeares ruler of that common wealth, heard one a whole day wrangling and reviling him; provoking him from the word to the ſword; and when the curriſh fellow had done barking,</hi> Pericles <hi>lighted him home with a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne. You are inraged, you will anſwer the Duell; I will but light you with a lanthorne, that you may ſee what a foule thing you goe about; how iniurious to your ſelfe, to your King, to your country: how you make your ſelfe a meere childe in ſuffering your ſelfe to be led by the ſleeve to the field like a babie: you make your ſelfe a Bedlam by running into furie and frenzie: Did you deſire Honour, to be thought valiant; I doe here ſhew you wherein true Honour, and true Valour doth conſiſt: if yet ye will leave the true for the ſhadow, and being hungry, will chooſe painted meates before the wholeſome; blame not me for warning you, before you fill your ſelfe with winde, which will ſhame you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You will tell me I preſume, when I talke of valour: it is out of my element, valour is in the higheſt region of the fire, and I in low water, cold, ſnowy, the point of the penne, ever hath had ſmall acquaintance with the poynt of the weapon: none but Eagles can look on bright valours rayes: I am but an Owle that flyeth by night, and uſe not the world by day light, where when mens courages riſe up, there muſt bee ruſhing to whet them, elſe manhood will grow ruſtie. I commend in you the care of valour, keepe it, but looſe not your wits, keepe altogether and know from me; ſome may want skill to uſe their weapons and not want knowledge to uſe courage, and to teach you.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177091:8"/> Gladiatores perfectiſſimos <hi>(ſaith</hi> Tertullian) non tantum magiſtri, ſed etiam Idiotae quique adhortan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertull. ad Mar. c.</hi> 2.</note> de longinquo, et ſaepe de ipſo populo dictata, ſuggeſta profuerint, <hi>you moſt expert ſwordmen,</hi> Gladia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores perfectiſſimos, <hi>call me Ideot in armes:</hi> Idiote, <hi>but yet, confeſſe a meane skill, can tell you in your eare ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that will doe you good, when your ſwords are cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing:</hi> de ipſo populo ſuggeſta profuerint.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Schooleman.</head>
               <p>I <hi>Have affected brevity, becauſe I ſpeake vnto paſsion, that never ſtayeth long to heare any thing. I come not often to the ſchoole for the definition of things, thats too fine a thread for bleere-eyed quarellers to looke on: it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth me to have a quiet word with plaine reaſon, not caring much for formality in perſwaſion, which it ſelfe indeed is not much in uſe (as men uſe to ſay now a dayes) in a Nation that ſo little ſuffereth to bee perſwaded to any thing, though fondly led to moſt things, by creatures of no choice, not by any good quality, but by a kinde of fancie: Preachings and perſwaſions, ſay many, may be found for any caprich: as if reaſoning were a kinde of Iugling, faſt and looſe, or that becommed not rationall creatures, to be led by reaſon, no more then to bee led by the noſe: Men clayme not that name, untill they can leade themſelves; the</hi> Cannot <hi>becomes onely women and children. I run often upon Examples, becauſe they delight longer, and move ſtronger: of what we ſee other worthies have done, perchance wee may take to doe ſomething, whiles wee will</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177091:8"/> 
                  <hi>be perſwaded to nothing; in matter of knowledge, our own muſt ever be the beſt, becauſe (as we pretend) we ſee cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, we ſee preſidents: and there are faſhions of paſsions, as well, as of apparell, which the power of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will have followed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the Common wealths-man.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT is you that ſit in gowns; that muſt overrule weapons:</hi> cedant arma togae. <hi>I dare not require my penne to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cic. in epiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>reach unto</hi> Vertue, <hi>that were to bee ieered at: I aske but</hi> Order, <hi>and aske no more, but what a civill common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth muſt grant me: I pray aſsiſtance. If you bid me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect, that boyling youth, &amp; their fiery vayns, are not yet fit, for the ſtill muſick of the heavens, I know it; yet in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kingdomes the God of this world gathereth up brave youth in cluſters; whiles indeede in ſome countries hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven findes but a poore picking: let hot ſpurs in theſe infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour orbes, where ſo much ſtriving and ſtruggling is for meanes &amp; manners, feele what is for the beſt advantage of the univerſe: ſo grace them, and make you them wear the diamond of valour, now and then, with a foyle, I ſay not of Piety, but of Chriſtianity: your wiſdomes bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to effect it. If men muſt now and then, hew one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers limmes; yet let them not goe on, like wilde beaſts; of theſe, their fights and Fates end together, and have no after reckonings: but men muſt come again before a iuſt God; therefore helpe them to keepe good quarter: and you that are the Treaſurers of the Commonwealth, increaſe your treaſure, give them a good</hi> behaviour, <hi>which may keepe them, ſo they will keepe it: binde them to</hi> Peace, <hi>and I will end, and hold mine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177091:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177091:9"/>
            <head>To the courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, it was the authors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to have preſented thee with a compleat receit for the cure of this bloudy fluxe, wherewith the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants of our age are too muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered, but ſome intervenient occaſions unhappily diverting the current of his endevours to another courſe, hee hath not beene able to comply with his earneſt deſires, yet having already prepared ſome few ſheets for the preſſe, hee judged it not inconvenient to communicate them with thee, as an eſſay and pledge of what he intendeth to perfect hereafter: hoping they may prove as ſometimely preparatives, to aſſwage and mitigate the ſharpe and corroſive humours, wherewith many hearts are unnaturally tormented. And if he ſhall find the ſucceſſe in this kinde to be in any reaſonable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree correſpondent to his deſires and expectation. I make no queſtion, but he will eſteeme their eaſe not onely a ſufficient recompenſe for his forepaſſed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, but alſo a forcible encouragement for their further cure, to accompliſh that which ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth
<pb facs="tcp:177091:10"/> unperfect. The fruits whereof thou mayeſt expect this next terme: till when and ever, I wiſh thou mayeſt enioy thy ſelfe in perfect peace and patience: which is no leſſe my deſire, than the Authors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177091:10"/>
            <head>Section I. <hi>Reaſon Pleadeth againſt the cuſtome of Duelling.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>The firſt founders of duells were baſe Creatures.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>By duell-Law, wiſe men muſt follow fooles.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Strength, can be no triall of truth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>To enter a Duell, is to turne theefe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>The Dueller, alwayes miſtakes his enemy.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Vellers are fraught, with moſt violent paſſion: therefore, they muſt needs bee voydeſt of reaſon. Reaſon is a light, Paſſion is darkeneſſe: what is more contrary to light then darkeneſſe? Hence, I finde Duelliſme, though it creepe into uſe, can bee but a blinde cuſtome. Some men will affect a cuſtome, for their reſpect due to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner of it: in that, may appeare reaſon: but ſee, who were the firſt deviſers of Duells.</p>
            <div n="1" type="point">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:177091:11"/>
               <head>Point. 1.</head>
               <head type="sub">Plea. 1. <hi>The firſt founders of Duells were baſe Creatures.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DVells and Devils begun together. <hi>Lucifer</hi> conceited himſelfe the better creature, and would not give wall to man made of a mould-hill: hee worded the matter, with the maſter, ſtept to his face, <hi>Aſcendam,</hi> and told him to his teeth, <note place="margin">Eſay. 14.</note> he was as good as God: <hi>Similis ero altiſsimo:</hi> upon this quarrell, <hi>Lucifer</hi> and <hi>Michael</hi> met, with their ſeconds: the valiant Archangell (with leave) came to cloſe <note place="margin">Apoc. 12.</note> fight: and the lawleſſe challenger <hi>Lucifer,</hi> with his ſeconds fell. Here lye the firſt Duellers, and their fortune. After theſe quarrelling ſpirits were ſent to hell: I heare no more of combats, till the faſhion of Cowards came in.</p>
               <p>Cowards and chalengers, came hand in hand into the world together. Scarce had God made ground, for men to worke upon: when <hi>Cain,</hi> an idle fellow, that had many obligations at home, yet ſpent his time all abrode in hunting: whileſt <hi>Abell,</hi> his youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brother did play the good husband: and therefore the Lord loved him, <hi>Cain</hi> hates him, and makes it a quarrell. <hi>Cain</hi> will prove himſelfe the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> man by a combat: when good men be all gone, <hi>Cain</hi> hopeth to come into election. Like a wretched Coward he inveagles Abell to the field, <hi>eamus in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:177091:11"/> without weapon: and ſuddenly ſets upon him, and kils him. Here I ſhew you the next dueller.</p>
               <p>So Duelliſme brings its badge of infamy, even from the beginning; Inquire the worthies, whom maintainers of Duels doe imitate, you will finde but Devills and Cowards. Therefore let noble ſpirits, yeeld thus farre unto reaſon, that Duelliſme in the cradle, deſerves no love, for the fathers ſake: and let us goe nearer it, to looke if reaſon will affoord any better regard for its owne merits.</p>
               <p>Duell law is, that differences muſt be tryed by the weapon: as wrongs will all the yeare bee budding, ſo men muſt ever be bleeding. Duelliſme, is a game; where you ſhuffle ſwords, and the maddeſt gameſter hath ever the leading: ſo that, one maine thing in this hot ſporte, is, that wiſemen muſt follow fooles. If a fellow gaze at noone and ſweare it is night, nay will ſweare it by the ſunne that ſhines, and ſay you lye if you deny it, and challenge you, and goe to the field, why, there goes a foole: and you muſt follow him: elſe by ſtaying at home, you looſe your honour, and where? nay I cannot tell, nor you nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where you had it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="point">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:177091:12"/>
               <head>Point. 2.</head>
               <head type="sub">Plea. 2. <hi>By Duell-law wiſemen muſt follow fooles.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVIll you ſee, two wiſe challenge-makers, ſtuffed with honour, as a gooſe with groates? which is but for wiſe men to <note place="margin">Relatum mihi a ſide digni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> feed on: Both were big-lookt ſouldiers: our happy age did bring them: the lofty low-countryes did breed them: amongſt the moſt warlike troupes of Europe. The one ſet to dice, and proved unlucky; his mony being out, his mettle got up, &amp; from dicing, he would needs to duelling, but wanted matter: he ſpies on his owne head a blacke hat, hee caſts that downe bravely, and ſweares it is white. This champion fights not now, for the beauty of his miſtris, but for his old hat: if any dare gaine ſay him; he doth chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, and will kill: thus he crakes up and downe, like a gander. The reſt of the flocke, were fluttering in their game, and ſo the challenge ſtayeth unanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Till anon, another of the hopefull company, was caſt away on the ſame ſhoare, the waves or the knaves had ſwallowed up his mony: and away ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth he to give a croſſe challenge, for now hee that was fooled out of his mony, he was in the right cue of a Dueller: he will challenge; and fight, and kill, and lookes blacke: and all, to maintaine the hat was blacke.</p>
               <p>Iuſt, our Duellers now adayes: much to the like,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177091:12"/> or leſſer purpoſe, our quarrells: for a falſe ſmile of a beauty; a ſimple conceit, of ſome hollow friend: a light miſtake of a foe, things all of no value, a challenge muſt paſſe, muſt have its anſwer: elſe honour goe exiled for ever. That ſuch men are not wiſe, I ſay not: but ſurely, to be a follower of ſuch men, is a very poore ſervice, for honour.</p>
               <p>If a Bedlame in knowne attire, armes naked, and cap-feathered, challenge you, to hurle your ſelfe downe a rocke, and breake your necke: though hee leade to the bottome upon the ſame termes, ſhall you be termed a Coward, if you follow him not? In Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, if thoſe grave Senates, were challenged by plaintiffes; muſt all the Iudges, riſe ftom the Bench, runne to cutlers and buy ſwords, thence to S. <hi>Iames</hi> his fields: and make of their bookes bucklers? what confuſion of mankinde? would not this heavily be cenſured in Starre chamber, that ſuch able men, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch weake ones? And is it not, as puniſhable; when men by their blood, of great worth: by their nature, of excellent wit: by their experience, of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar wiſdome: doe caſt all theſe good merits, into the flame of a Duell, only becauſe ſome inconſiderate man doth challeng them Valour, ſhould ever thinke it baſe, to lye open, unto every ones anger: to wait at a mad-caps heeles, to bee at hand whenſoever he calls to the field: there ought to be a greater diſtance, betweene courage and folly, betweene greatneſſe and weakeneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12 of <hi>France,</hi> when in a lower fortune, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ypſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. Polit. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:177091:13"/> he was but Duke of <hi>Orleance,</hi> ſuffered a great abuſe from ſome peeres, and was throughly ſenſible there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he minded to right himſelfe by his weapon, and reach his enemy to the heart: the meane time advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him from a Dukedome (of <hi>Orleance,)</hi> to a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, of <hi>France,</hi> and now ſitting ſoe high, hee hath quite loſt the ſight of quarrell: hee fancieth not any feeling of it: his nobles, friendly remember him, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge himſelfe: no ſaith <hi>Lewis. Parum de corum eſt regi Galliarum iniurias illatas Aurelianorum ducibus ulciſci;</hi> it becomes not a king to take up ſo low a quarrell: that were, to wreath the Scepter with diſgrace, to hang the crowne upon infamy. The affront did call, but upon a Duke, <hi>Iniurias Aurelianorum ducibus illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> why ſhall a king follow it? when the creature which offends, is but meane, and is too baſe, for a Lion-courage to prey upon?</p>
               <p>Thus you (if you hold your ſelfe worthy) ſhould diſcourſe with your ſelfe; when you are called to combat, ſay you will not ſtir, not becauſe you are too weake, but becauſe you are too great: what lyeth too far below us, is as far out of our reach, as what is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced too far aboue us; caſt a ſtone at the ſtars, they will not ſend you a challenge by night, they cannot fight with ſuch Lownes as you: They know their glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y is too high for you to blemiſh, or hope to offend: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they can have no cauſe to be angry with you. So you know your ſelfe, to be a bright ſtar of valour, a ſparke of the planet <hi>Mars,</hi> and ſcorne to come neere little ones. If a childe revile you; will you cite him,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177091:13"/> wilde to the field? why, quarrelling duellers, are but children; they know no more where they ſet their feet when they goe to the field, no more to governe themſelves, nor their weapons, then if they were ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies; and it were good, the nurſe ſhould ſwadle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine their armes up, they uſe them ſo crookedly; they will never keepe their fingers out of their mouths, all the ſtrength of their armes hangs ſtill at their tongues end. O Gentlemen of worth and of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour! when you are by ſome fiery hot-ſpur chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to the field, ſay with King <hi>Lewis, Parum decorum eſt ulciſci,</hi> looke upon the greatneſſe of your owne valour, and doe not abuſe it, by uſing it ſo meanely. It is cowardly: a man, all cloathed in ſteele, to draw upon a man naked? I hold it worſe, a man fortified with valour, to ſet upon a weakeling quareller? it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a weakeneſſe of ſtomacke to turne ſoure at every morſell: and quarelling ſpirits are certainely of the ſofteſt kinde of mettall; every little touch doth ſo bruſe them, that they will leake bloud preſently. The worthier you are, the leſſe warrant you will ſtill find, to follow a quareller to the field: which ponderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Holy court.</note> moved <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> that moſt valiant and victorious Prince, Prudently to refuſe <hi>Marke Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> his raſh and indiſcreet defiance, commanding the challenge-bearer for to tell <hi>Anthony,</hi> that when hee was weary of his life, he could find other more noble meanes to be deprived of it, then in hazarding it with <hi>Anthony</hi> in ſingle combat: ſo (that is much to bee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented) this baſe combating humour, hath ſo farre
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177091:14"/> crept into honour, and that it lurkes moſt in good blood: whileſt the infection, cannot ſpread amongſt meaner Perſons; it ſeemes theſe are grown to a ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger conſtitution of manhood.</p>
               <p>This was it: the wiſeman teaching to our times, <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10. 7.</note> ſo much wondered at: <hi>Vidi</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>ſervos in equis, Principes ambulantes in terra,</hi> A ſtrange ſight! I ſee a meane man, hot in paſſion, provoked mightily by his foe, growne ſo furious, that you would iudge rage runneth away with him beyond all reaſon: and yet hee handles the raines of his paſſion ſo well, hee keeps his ſaddle ſure that hee falls not, <hi>vidi ſervos in equis:</hi> he holds ſtill that command over himſelfe, that none can draw him a Duelling: he feeles, it muſt be his owne undoing: in purſute of his right: hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales ſtill, from his owne arme, unto a court of iuſtice. And yet, thoſe that weare honour out at the elbowes: and the world cals, its beſt men: at the very firſt guird of anger, looſe their ſtirrops, and reele, <hi>vidi Principes in terra:</hi> they follow they know not whither, any paſſionate man, that will lead them: and willfully, will carry their wrongs, to triall byſteele, contemning all legall cauſes, as though, all gentlemens rights, muſt admit of no other <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> but the rapier.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="point">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:177091:14"/>
               <head>Point. 3.</head>
               <head type="sub">Plea. 3. <hi>Strength, can bee no triall of truth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis giddy Duelling: is no fruit of honour, it is the worme of honour: a fit of falling ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of manhood: when reaſon, is out of doores, and ſoules are caſt, quite paſt their ſenſes. But will you come to your ſelfe; and heare reaſon! Your enemy, offended you; why, ſo he did the law too; then let law puniſh him, for you both, rather leave the weapon, to the ſtronger hand: let law anſwer the challenge; ſo will you bee ſure to revenge, your king will be your ſecond.</p>
               <p>If you grow out of love, with kings lawes: and to come by your right, you will call no iury, but fury: whoſoever makes of you (as you ſay) an aſſe, you will make of him an oxe, and knocke him in the head. Let us then, pull <hi>Littletons</hi> quoyfe over his eyes, and turne the blinde foole out of Weſtminſter: we will make that hall, a goodly ſhambles: of Inns of Courts, we will deviſe fencing ſchooles: and will have, no more aſſiſes: all care muſt be, to finde out a luſty butcher, that can knocke downe readily. Whoſoever, hath beſt skill in armes, ſhall have beſt right, to others lands: (wee will have a new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt) if you deny, the ſtrongeſt mans right; hee ſhall give you the lye, and boare a hole in your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177091:15"/> and that way come into poſſeſſion. The trueſt tongue, ſhall ever grow neereſt the luſtieſt ſhoulders: and from the ſtouteſt mouth, you muſt alwayes ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther verities: Nay, wee will paſſe into trades: the valianteſt taylor, ſhall doe your worke, ſo you may goe out of faſhion: the luſtieſt maſon, ſhall bee your layer, ſo your houſe may fall on your head. And ſuch be the conſequences of unruly courage.</p>
               <p>Theſe like tenets, are too mad; to paſſe for currant, amongſt men. One will fight, will kill, to prove himſelfe the valianter man; that is no good conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. It may be your enemy his foote failed him, not his heart, he ſtumbled; ſo you killed him: His weapon forſooke him, not hee, the action; ſo you overtooke him. The wrenching of a ſinew, hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the right rule of his ſword, whereby you got within him: ſo, you reached him his deadly wound. And thus, the valianter man; ofttimes dyeth.</p>
               <p>Goe on: and let us heare, your further diſcourſe: your enemie gave you the lie, therefore you will fight, you will kill him; to prove that your ſelfe ſpeakes, more truth then he: That is a worſe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: ſtrength of body, and true dealing, fall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a ſunder: if every word, the ſtrong man ſpeakes, muſt paſſe for currant truth: that Ancient, was a very foole, which firſt invented <hi>a Polyphemus;</hi> a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtrong fellow, and yet with one eye onely: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted, with ſtrong limbs, and weake ſight: a face, with a ſingle Eye, and it out of the way, in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177091:15"/> in this pendent-haire faſhion now a dayes, hee would be alwayes hud-winked. Surely <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> had done great miſchiefe to the world, in putting out that one eye, had hee not preſently knocked out his braines: for, we ſhould have had, a fellow as blinde as a betle, moſt ſtrong, moſt powerfull, and ſo turne teacher of every body: for, all truth, muſt be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from his mouth, his lips only keepes the treaſure of wiſedome: from him, wee muſt take new do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, new councels, new cuſtomes, and every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy muſt beleeve him, after his eyes be out, elſe every body muſt be knocked in the head; becauſe, hee is ſtrong enough to do it.</p>
               <p>If ſtrength muſt thus maintaine truth: then let us reſolve firſt, who is the ſtrongeſt man in a countrey; let that man prate at pleaſure; faire mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens muſt owe unto him, their good names: and gentlemen their good bloud. If you once finde the ſtrongeſt man of a kingdome: hee may freely geere, and diſcourſe. Let him ſay; there is no honour, in peace: no valour, in warre: Captaines, be but kettles, of baſe extraction: ſome, forced, for feare of the pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hookes, to hang over the fire of warre; as not able, at home, to keepe open kitchings. Others, often, boyle ever; they inrich themſelves, ſo faſt. Moſt, the rather maintaine fire of diſſention about them, to have meat within them. Let him ſay: that men, are but frogs in ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and dublet: quackers, that women are but bundles of doubts, moved up and downe by the winde fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kers. Let him ſay: there is, no inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177091:16"/> upon earth: no kings, in the ſtocke: no great cards, but coted knaues; ſome bigger, ſome leſſer, ſome thinner in cloathes, ſome mufled in larger gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and knaves all, that ſhuffle the queances, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. And all this, muſt be ſo: nay, though, as he denyeth a king on earth, ſo hee deny unto the heaven, a godhead.</p>
               <p>And all this muſt bee true, becauſe hee is the moſt ſtrong man, that ſaith ſo: and will challenge you, if you deny it: and proves all by the ſword, as by a moſt bright argument. Is not all this, againſt reaſon? when ſtrength carrieth away truth, what ſhall poore women have? they muſt ſpeake never a true word; and ſo their amorous ſwordmen, ſhall have worke e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to make, for every lye, a quarrell.</p>
               <p>O Inconſiderate Duellers, will no reaſon force you, to put up your weapons? but ſtill, they play, to gaine you honour: then, take this point; they can win you, no honour, but what muſt be ſtayned, with Infamy. I know, honour and wealth, are things in great price. But hearke; a tall fellow, that never ſowed, will now gather wealth upon the highwayes: and you, like it not: ſuch moneyes, come in baſely; who will have them ſo muſt be a theefe: why no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe you, the honour which you get by murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, is as baſe; when you duellize, you latronize: when you project combats, you doe noe otherwiſe then as in an honeſt neighbourhood, to turne theefe: and who protects you, is no better, then a receiver of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="point">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:177091:16"/>
               <head>Point. 4.</head>
               <head type="sub">Plea. 4. <hi>To enter a Duell is to turne Theefe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN a Duell, what doe you ſtrive for? life: why, that is not yours: when you rob a man of his life, you ſteale it; then if you goe a combating, you goe a ſtealing. You kill your enemy, you expoſe your ſelfe, to be killed; why, you diſpoſe of things, none of your owne; that is but a tricke of a theefe. Your life, God hath given it, to your king; and unto you, but the loane of it: the king keepes it, for his owne turne; you may take the uſe of it, in your owne affaires, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly during the kings pleaſure: when the king cals for it, to the warre, or his other ſervice, you muſt carry it: is it not then, againſt all reaſon, that you ſhould ſpoyle your life when you will? May one murther himſelfe in the field? no heathen dare ſay it: why, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can you carry your ſelfe to field, to be murthered by any other: you are acceſſary to both crimes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually; a ſtranger, ſhould have, rather leſſe power over your life, then you have your ſelfe; ſo, you foule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtake, in concurring with any, to kill you. You will call any priuate man, theefe, that drives but a beaſt off your ground, and ſels it: that takes, againſt your will, but a cruſt out of your houſe, and caſts it to the dog: and will not you call him a worſer
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177091:17"/> theefe, that ſnatcheth a ſoule, out of a living body, and caſts it perchance to the divell.</p>
               <p>Your life is not your owne; God keepes it for his owne uſe; there are two Ioint lords of your life; God, and Caeſar; God will have you, to liue longer, to pay him ſervices: God, is Lord of the Honour: and he will have you live a longer terme. Gods bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reaſon, warneth you, that it is not fit, you ſhould remove out of Gods f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alty, diſreſpectfully: you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not leave Gods ſervice ſuddenly, at your pleaſure, or diſpleaſure; take heed, it will beare an action, in the leet of heaven.</p>
               <p>This reaſon, was ſo ſtrong, that in a great uprore, it held the courage, of the valiant <hi>Weneſlaus</hi> king of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> in very good order. His brother <hi>Bodeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus,</hi> ſet upon him furiouſly, ſtriking with every blow to kill: king <hi>Weneſlaus</hi> manfully defending himſelfe, unweaponed his brother, whom ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding now upon the ground, when the waves of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in <hi>Weneſlaus,</hi> would have ſwallowed up <hi>Bodeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus,</hi> when iuſt furie did cry, kill and revenge. At that inſtant, reaſon ſtrikes in, and <hi>Weneſlaus</hi> reflects, what hee is going about: to take away, a life, unto which indeed he hath right, becauſe he is <hi>Caeſar;</hi> but yet God hath alſo a right unto it; and therefore, <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſlaus</hi> reſolveth to meddle no further with it: but ſheatheth his ſteele, and ſaith thoſe golden wordes: <hi>mallem ut fraterdeo ſanguinis reddat rationem, quam ſi ego in fratrem manus iniecero, et fratris necis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uſam apud</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Polit.</note> 
                  <hi>Deum dicere compellerer.</hi> I will not adventure to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177091:17"/> ſteale out of the world a life, for the which, in a higher court, one day, I muſt come to triall: let my brother, keepe his life, and anſwer in Court himſelfe, for it.</p>
               <p>Why will not ſubiects, ſubmit unto reaſon, that forced ſo mighty a prince: when they bee called to combats, may they not without bluſhing, ſpeake af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo warlike a king, and refuſe, leaſt <hi>necis cauſam apud deum dicere compellerer.</hi> I will not runne away with mens lives, and have a puniſhing God at my heeles. But our Duellers will gather liues, as leaves: and mow mens heads, with aſmuch pleaſure, as husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men doe their meadowes. Neither God nor king, ſhall keepe them from killing men, they will drinke bloud to coole their choler: and rather then want it, they will goe ſo farre out of all reaſon, that they will take the lives of thoſe that neuer offended them: they will bereaue innocency, of its poſſeſſion: it ſeemes they will fight, for no other cauſe, but to ſhew they can kill.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="point">
               <head>Point. 5.</head>
               <head type="sub">Plea. 5. <hi>The Dueller miſtakes alwayes his enemy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HOw often, hath it happened<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that in a ſudden diſtaſte, you miſtook your iniurer; you ſtruck, &amp; did not touch, the man that wronged you. Let reaſon, here in a corner, talke with you a little, of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177091:18"/> things out of fight. Wee all know, wee have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne Foes; and a boſome enemie ſtill bites nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the heart: a wound, leaſt in eye, is moſt in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. To open the truth to you; the Devill is your greateſt enemie, hee brought the man, which you terme your abuſer, to the Ale-houſe; to ſquabble with you, there: doe not then challenge the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, but charge the Devill: elſe, you miſtake your enemie; you uſe to ſay, you will fight with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; why ſtrike him now, when Man doth ſtrike you. More, it is drinke, that hath beene the brocher of all the quarrell, and hath ſtirred the man, againſt you: elſe, all had beene quiet: then turne the drinke, up and downe the floore, and tumble not the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard: but pitie, to ſee, how the Devill plies him with fire and water, with furie and ſmall Ale.</p>
               <p>If you doe otherwiſe; you are ſo farre out of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that you turne an irrationall creature: you turne Cur: <hi>Simile quiddam canibus admittis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Baſil,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. hom. de ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> of the quarrelling man, <hi>qui ſaxa mordere ſolent, non jactantes:</hi> Caſt a ſtone at a dog, and how quick he will meet it in the field! what a combat, what a gnawing, what a pawing; O had the dog but a ſword by his ſide, what a brave Dueller hee would make! And all the while of this doggiſhneſſe, there is no looking, where is the man that did hurt the dog, no notice taken of the hand that moved the ſtone to ſet at the dog, and did all the miſchiefe.</p>
               <p>So you Duellers: You uſe a juſt dog-trick, when you carrie your ſelves ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>iſhly towards him tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:177091:18"/> thumpes you with heavie words: it is true, hee it is, whoſe breath doth touch you: it is him, you feele: and from whom commeth your ſmart: yet he is, but the ſtone, and very like it, blinde and heavy: reflect then, there is another hand, which doth throw him at you, which wheeles him, and violently caſts him upon you. Therefore in all reaſon, <hi>in hunc hominum interfectorem, iram transfer:</hi> the Divell is the iniurer, and faine would be your murtherer, <hi>hominum inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectorem:</hi> therefore, turne all your hatred upon the Divell: it is crafty Sathan, that ſets on a fellow blinde with paſſion, to anger you; take pitty, to ſee, how the divell playes upon him, making him a blocke to lie in your way to ſtumble at, <hi>fratris in te peccantis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerere,</hi> commiſerate, when you feele him under you, remembring it was the divell, that laid him there.</p>
               <p>Doth your enemie abuſe you in a publique mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, doth hee invite you to a boſome full of your bloud? <hi>aliquis te infeſtat</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> is he very peeviſh with you? yet looke not after him, <hi>in ipſum ne reſpice,</hi> it is not worth your labour; you will never come that way within reach of him that did you the wrong <hi>in daemonem inſtigantem iram funde,</hi> ingage your rage, your courage, in ſetting upon the Divell. You may arme your ſelfe with weapons of proofe; wherewith you may anger him: be but patient and meeke, you will fret him mightily: be humble, you give him a great buffet; uſe any goodneſſe, and you will ſtabbe his very heart; keepe but one graine of grace, and hee dare never tarry with you. Why will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177091:19"/> you not then, lay downe your ſword, wherwith you miſtake your enemie, and take up ſome better wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, wherewith you might beat the divell your murtherer.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee, how Duelliſme, is every way againſt reaſon: the dueller miſtakes his maſters, they bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, cowards, or fooles: he miſtakes his way; to the triall of truth: hee miſtakes himſelfe, to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a theefe: and laſtly, he miſtakes his enemy: and having miſtaken himſelfe ſo many waies, hee run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth yet into further miſtakings; hee doth miſtake his God, for hee goeth about to ſet up a new Deitie, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o heave the true God out of heaven.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:177091:19"/>
            <head>Section II. <hi>It is prime valour, to put off Challenges, and to ſuffer.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>Either,</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>To ſhun the greater harme.</hi> Or,</item>
               <item>2. <hi>To be maſter of your owne courage.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>To reſerve your valour for weightier imployments.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>To overcome your ſelfe.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no ſpeaking to ſome Sparks. Men are many times of ſo ſtubborne Spirits, that God himſelfe, let him ſay any thing contrarie to their mindes, rather than endure it, they will doe themſelves a miſchiefe. A Hot Spurre, before hee will beare a ſmall diſtaſte one houre, will breake his owne necke for ever.</p>
            <p>God forbade a luſtie Captaine, to taſte a Honey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb <note place="margin">1 Reg. 14. 27.</note> which hung in a tree: he ſnuft at it, and grew diſtempered: he apprehended it unworthy ſo tall a Fellow, to be checkt like a Childe, not eat but with licence; and hee lifted up his Truncheon, (againſt God) touched the Honey, bearing it to his lips, ſo, pitifully mildewing a plentifull Harveſt of victories, and blaſting the future ſprings of all his flouriſhing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177091:20"/> fortunes. Who could imagine a Souldier, would ſo much to his loſſe, ſtrive with God for a licke of Honey?</p>
            <p>From a great Queene, God tooke but one Apple: <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 17.</note> and yet left it her growing, to beautifie her Garden: But charged her, not to eat it; God reſerved it, for his owne diſh: he adviſed her, not to minde it: ſhee termed that a ſcorne of her ſoveraignty, to chide her fancie; quarrelled with God about it, and heaped a world of ſorrowes and wants, unto her ſelfe and all her children. Who would beleeve, a Queene of the earth, to contend with the King of Heaven for an apple? But read the Chronicles of Paleſtine, and ſee <note place="margin">Gen. 3 16.</note> what befell them both, for ſtriving with their betters; and learne thereby to goe ſlowly into diſtaſtes againſt your greater.</p>
            <div n="1" type="point">
               <head>Point 1.</head>
               <head type="sub">Suffer. 1. <hi>It is true valour, to ſuffer, when you muſt loſe, by ſtriving.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is prime valour, oft times, to ſuffer: for no other reaſon, but becauſe one that is above you, (by Scepter, or Crozier, by might, or craft) will have you ſuffer; and you cannot hinder it, but by doing your ſelfe more hurt, than all your ſuffering can mount unto: in ſuch a caſe, I ſay, true valour doth bid you, not ſeeke revenge, but force your ſelfe to ſuffer: you ſhew ſtoutneſſe, to dare look an abuſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177091:20"/> in the face, and not to ſqueale out at the firſt touch of it. You call it courage, to ſubmit to the Surgeons knife, when a diſeaſe hath made him your Maſter: ſo if your weakneſſe makes a meane man way to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter you, you ſhew good metall, when you let him cut you: for you fence ſtill a greater miſchiefe off, with a leſſer: and prove, it reſteth in no enemies power, to lay on you what load he pleaſe: you will take up your owne burthen; that is manlike. To live free from all ſufferings, were to live beyond the rate of mortall men: a meane Cottenger makes oft times a mightie man ſuffer. The difference betweene valiant and cowardly ſpirits I finde is, that valour will be ſtill his owne carver; whileſt cowards doe gape, like Cewetts, when you bob them under the chin. The ſtout man can for his advantage, hold his own ſnarliſh noſe to the Grindſtone, when it growes too ſharp, and dull the edge of honour: hee will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a laſh of diſgrace, or diſcontent, to get free from a more burthenſome evill: and to winde himſelfe into a better occaſion, to get his right, to puniſh his abuſer, and not abuſe himſelfe too.</p>
               <p>Certainely, men ought not to be ſo pettiſh with God and man: meanes ſhould be uſed, to bring ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a little more into credit and practice: ſuffer a great man, ſometimes, be it but for his greatneſſe. If great God, will take from you your honey, your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, your apple, your profit; ſtrive not therefore; you and God grow not to be enemies. A greater, a craftier, a peeviſher man than your ſelfe, will have
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177091:21"/> ſome of your ancient rights from you: why, if hee will needs ſnatch them, be not preſently a ſtruggling; beat him not out of breath, with drie blowes of bags of money: if you waſte your treaſure in Law, ſo you joyne with your enemie to undoe you: never fetch a golden fee over the barre at Weſtminſter, becauſe a great man leaps over your hedge a hunting: fence not a little harme off with a mightie one: that is not to be <hi>Prudentes ſicut Serpentes;</hi> upon everie diſtaſte <note place="margin">Matth. 10. 16.</note> be not a ſtriving. A great heart may ſtand a time under a great burthen of wrongs, and the ſtouteſt ſhoulders riſe not upon the legs that are the quickeſt kickers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> was a man of good ranke in the world, <note place="margin">Gen. 12. 1.</note> and had great wealth, a faire houſe, certaine and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demeanes in Vr and Haran: his Land-Lord God, upon a ſmall warning turnes him out a doores, ſets houſe and lands over his head to another. <hi>Abraham</hi> is ſilent, he never queſtioneth God in the high Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie of his mercies. <hi>Abraham</hi> knew his time to ſuffer, And he ſuffereth more yet; Hee hath but one ſonne, upon whom hee had bravely builded the hopes of a <note place="margin">Gen 22. 2.</note> mirth of poſteritie, all the comfort of thoſe ages: God will needs make a Calfe of this Sonne, and knock him on the head, as a Victime unto the Almightie. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> carrieth his ſonne to the ſlaughter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caius Caeſar</hi> had a ſubject ſtout, wealthy, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable: he was of the order of Knights, the onely Nobilitie of thoſe ages, when Dukes now deny, Kings claim'd no place at the ſide of the Scepter.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177091:21"/> This noble Knight was father to a hopefull Heire, &amp; was Owner of a Spaniſh mettall, which ever bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the beſt ſteele: his name was <hi>Paſtor,</hi> and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Lipſius</hi> obſerveth ſome of that name at this day in Spaine. This <hi>Paſtors</hi> eldeſt ſonne was undeſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called to execution by the angrie Emperour <hi>Caius:</hi> the father hath both love to feele, and valour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, yet ſtriveth not againſt the potent Prince, but ſuffereth his ſonne to dye: and beares it out ſo cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, that betweene his words and thoughts you could not ſpie a ſorrow: <hi>Nec dolorem aliquo ſigno erumpere paſſus eſt. Paſtor</hi> is mightily ſenſible, and yet you perceive him not diſcontented. If you aske him how his ſonnes wrongfull death goeth downe with him ſo gently? why is his ſtoutneſſe ſo pliable to ſuffer? <hi>Seneca</hi> anſwereth you for him wittily, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor</hi> had another ſonne to loſe, <hi>Habuit alterum. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, cap.</hi> 33.</note> did ſuffer, to ſave himſelfe from greater ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings: the Knight had more yet to loſe, therefore his beſt courſe was to be quiet: had he contended with his Prince, had he urged that mightie arme, it would but inlarge his harme: ſo <hi>Paſtor</hi> might have loſt all his children, and himſelfe too.</p>
               <p>Have you a few acres in a whole Mannor, or one Mannor amongſt many, which a neighbour great or covetous gapes after, and ſighes for ſorely? eaſe him and your ſelfe too, and let him take it; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times merrily, becauſe upon that ground, you will raiſe no unkindneſſes: remember with <hi>Paſtor, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes alterum,</hi> you have more lands to loſe; and if you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177091:22"/> cannot ſuffer one to rob you of this, in ſome by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way he will wait for you, he will ſet law upon you, to rob you of all the reſt. When ſuch a croſſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe muſt come into requeſt, deny it not; there is no cure, but to diet your choler, and walke out of the way of your conceit of honour: if you will goe to law, to anſwer a great mans gall, all your lands may ſinke in it: take therefore <hi>Paſtors</hi> counſell in time, ſuffer one loſſe, leſt you ſuffer many. Your childe, your wealth, your comfort, let it goe when mightie God will have it ſo: remember <hi>Habes alterum;</hi> if you be impatient, if your heart riſe, God will pick the reſt away from you. Your enemie hath gauled you, and <hi>Dulce eſt dolorem reddere,</hi> It is honey to you to cut his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seneca de Ira, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 32.</note> throat: loſe that honey, that ſweetneſſe of revenge, though you can reach it: ſay with <hi>Paſtor, Habes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum;</hi> you have a life to loſe, a quietneſſe of life to loſe, which is all the comfort of life; and if you ſtir to your enemie his loſſe, for your ſelfe, you muſt make another: therefore ſet your heart at reſt to ſuffer.</p>
               <p>You ſhall ſee <hi>Abraham</hi> ſuffer yet more: hee had a <note place="margin">Gen. 12 14, 15, 16.</note> wife, the Flower of all Aſia, that ever hath brought forth the primeſt Beauties: her face might have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amoured the Heavens. If the ancient amorous An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells any more were to come to court the <hi>filias homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> the Damoſells of <hi>Damaſeene,</hi> this beautifull creature would ſurely draw thoſe merrie Spirits from their Heavens: her prettie countenance was a clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of all the perfections of Nature: from her fame
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177091:22"/> 
                  <hi>Apelles</hi> afterwards ſtole all his neateſt features: when ſhe faded, her crimſon ſhe left to the Roſe, her can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor unto the ſnow, which in her kept heat enough to inflame millions. This woman being <hi>Abrahams</hi> wife, God bad him truſt her to court, thruſt her to the Kings boſome, and ſhee her ſelfe adventured the bed of a <hi>Pharo:</hi> yet <hi>Abraham</hi> made no quarrel againſt his God, nor againſt his conſort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſteth quiet: ſhee will be faithfull to the homely heardſman, amiddeſt the embraces of a king. Certainely, honeſt <hi>Abraham</hi> both had the Deſart to meet, and the happineſſe to injoy a moſt honeſt wife: hee beleeved God would keepe her.</p>
               <p>More: <hi>Abraham</hi> was a ſufferer, not onely of God, <note place="margin">Gen 13. v. 8. 9.</note> who he was ſure, could maſter him: but you ſhall ſee in him, towards mean men, a great deale of mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Abraham</hi> had a great ſtocke; his Coſen <hi>Lots</hi> ſhepheards, fenced up paſtures (for themſelves) and drove off <hi>Abrahams</hi> cattel: graſſe began to be ſhort, &amp; the hungry beaſts bellowed aloud for meat: <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> heart did ring with ſorrow; yet he held it quiet; he went not about to trie the title with <hi>Lot,</hi> by Law, nor armes, nor yet offered any blowes to the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards. But after a while goeth to <hi>Lots</hi> houſe, with hat in hand, <hi>obſecro,</hi> I pray faire dealing, without foule words: upon the goodly bankes, by theſe fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile brookes, in the ſhadie dales, there groweth graſſe in plentie; and wee have room enough for us both, therefore let us have no iuſling betweene us; <hi>Obſecro non fit jurgium inter nos;</hi> to what purpoſe ſhould we
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177091:23"/> two, goe to bore holes in one anothers skins, for our mony to drop thorow into the Surgeons fingers? wee are Coſens, let not miſ-beleevers cenſure the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the faithfull for moſt unkind: its true, a kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ought not to ſuffer too much from a kinſman, ſometimes ſuch may quarrel; but let us ſee firſt what cauſe we have to fight, and then we will trie, how we can fight it. I pray thee <hi>Lot,</hi> let us not kill our ſelves out of an humour, for a handfull of graſſe: wee are but ſtrangers in the countrie, and we are but two to ſtrengthen one another, let us not breake our backes to fill our beaſts bellies.</p>
               <p>All this pleading the matter was but a ſtaiedneſſe of <hi>Abrahams</hi> valour, no ſlowneſſe of his metall: <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> reflected upon inconveniences of greater conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and ſo withſtood his owne combating cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: for though you heare <hi>Abraham</hi> here a great ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer, you ſhall ſee him anon a great ſouldier; and know you hereby, that when you ſuffer, you be not preſently of the ſiſe of a coward; rather when you ſuffer to advantage your ſelfe, you ſhew a piece of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good manhood. About this ſame time, of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> crouching to his neighbour <hi>Lot,</hi> Kings in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon led martiall troopes abroad the countrey: and you ſhall ſee <hi>Abraham</hi> dare looke Kings in the face and beat them: five kings rove abroad and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, and one <hi>Abraham</hi> will be able to make a reſcue: <note place="margin">Gen. 14. v. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 16.</note> a few ſervants, a handfull of ſhepherds, led by an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham;</hi> do kill kings, rout troopes, returne ſpoiles, and fill the aire with applauſes of victory: ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177091:23"/> 
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> be a man of metall or no, and whether his ſuffering was his want of feeling, and of valour; no it was his judgement, to lead alwaies his courage un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his beſt advantage. O Dueller, you of the number of the faithfull? <hi>ſi filii Abraham eſtis, opera Abraham fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite;</hi> whom willingly you follow in faith, bee not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to follow in good manners: I like well, you be as <hi>Abraham</hi> was, with your weapon, a mighty do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; but I would have you alſo be, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was, at fit times, a meeke ſufferer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="point">
               <head>Point. 2.</head>
               <head type="sub">Suffer. 2. <hi>True valour is to be maſter of your owne courage, and not upon any ones call, to combat.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Obſerve, ſome men take wonderfull pleaſure in ſquabbling; therby they vaunt ſpirit, (which they cal) the touch-ſtone of generoſitie, they care not after what cauſe they go, ſo they carry it ſtoutly: this kind of courage, hangs ſometimes upon a good heart, yet it is not the fruit, it is but ſome little dead leafe that falls from the goodly plant of valour; or reckon it, as a moat amongſt the rayes of valour. The ſhining Sunne, will not be long without moats, it will finde them thorow one hole or other: it is as true, a man <note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> of bright and ſharpe mettal cannot belong without
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177091:24"/> meates, hee will fetch them ſtrangely out of corners. Yet that is not, becauſe the light doth like imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or valour love miſ-uſage; but becauſe, as moats doe follow the glorious Sunne, ſo ſome madneſſe doth ever follow manhood: <hi>nullum ingenium mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Sen. l. de Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quil. ſine.</note> 
                  <hi>ſine mixtura dementiae,</hi> ſcarce ſhall you meet a great courage, but it hath a little of unruly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; thoſe that can bridle it, are the moſt excellent men.</p>
               <p>Therefore, if you love credit, keepe your valour at a ſtand: ſuffer it not to ſtirre, untill it ſue firſt for leave; to the Queene of morall vertues, Prudence: ſo you ſhall truely be maſter of mettle, and not, your mettle maſter of you, that is not to be a man, but to be a ſlave of manhood, haled up and downe by met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleſome paſſions baſely. Theſe be harſh maſters, when they tyrannize over you. The greateſt skil of a ſword<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, is not to goe, but to ſtay to chuſe an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, to wrench it from his enemies in ſpite of them; elſe you are angry, but as the mouldy worpe, which with blinde furie biteth all it meets withall: if an offence cal on you and your anger riſe, bid it lie down againe, and ſleepe untill you awake it. Will you have your heart to be the centre of valour? then hold you quiet, when all the world flieth to pieces about you: for of all the earth, onely the centre can never be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caius Marius</hi> was undoubtedly of the beſt ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <note place="margin">The French Academy of Pierre de Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandie.</note> the Romane Militarie bred: hee was powerful in victories, hee hewed to peeces one hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177091:24"/> brave Low-countreymen in one battle: he was dreadfull to his foes, he put the rugged Cambriats to quicke flight, the noiſe of his name defeated many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. Yet when <hi>Paulus Sylla</hi> ſtept to his teeth and dared him to fight, <hi>Marius</hi> ſtands ſtill like a lambe: it was not becauſe <hi>Marius</hi> had loſt his mettle, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he held the reines of it, and would not ſuffer it runne after ſo ſilly a fellow as <hi>Sylla</hi> was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſeth the challenge, and ſaith, If <hi>Sylla</hi> holds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo tall a fellow, that hee can beat <hi>Marius,</hi> let him try to force <hi>Marius</hi> to fight in ſpite of his heart: for <hi>Sylla</hi> muſt know <hi>Marius</hi> maintaineth, hee will not fight, but when it pleaſe himſelfe. It is a greater ſtrength to hold backe the roaring Bull, than to run as faſt as he: nay it is much more might, to hold his ſtriving ſtrength quiet, than to fight with him. You Duellers, when you are called to the field, if you will be maſter of the field, ſtay your valour: looke upon <hi>Marius,</hi> who will draw upon no mans command, no mans challenging, no mans bidding: all challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers are but pratlers; to talke of fightings, and fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe unto <hi>Marius,</hi> are but tales of <hi>Robin-hood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Men of beſt valour themſelves know beſt, what time to fight: and the quarreller, with his humorous words, is no clocke for them to count by: they will not be tyed to keepe any mans houre: valour will be his owne chuſer, for time, place, and quarrell, and will hold nothing under its enemy; it will owe no ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and wil fight, but for what it ſelfe will. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is a moſt poore cuſtome, crept now adaies into
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177091:25"/> credit, that men muſt fight when they bee bidden, (when they be challenged) that is to make of men children. What difference betweene the cradle and gray haires? but that the one is carried (and ſo is the duell-anſwerer) the other walkes where hee pleaſe: the little one feeleth not where it goes, the great man knoweth hee hath great charge (of honour) about him, and therefore will take his owne time of the day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fabius Maximus</hi> the <hi>Non plus ultra,</hi> upon the Pillars <note place="margin">The French A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademy of Pierre de Primandy.</note> of the Romane Fortitude, had the command of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect troope, at the time <hi>Hannibal</hi> entred Italy; a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian ſouldier, thought it unworthy his ſo great a Commander lying in the way, the Garthaginian ſtandard ſhould approach the walls of Rome; and therfore with angry ſpeeches, attempted to rouſe the moſt mightie Generall <hi>Maximus</hi> to fight: but hee ſtirred not; all thoſe windes bluſtering f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om fooliſh lips, ſhaked no corn in <hi>Fabius</hi> his ears: <hi>Fabius</hi> ſaith, be wil ſhew valor, in that he wil not be drawn from his deliberation (which is to ſtay a convenienter time) not for all their tarring reproches: <hi>Fabius</hi> his valour runnes not out of ſight for a childs chaſing; his heart is no henne, that will be driven off the neſt (of his hopes) with a huſhing: that man is very weake hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that ſuffereth his heart, to runne away with him: that is but a convulſion of courage. <hi>Fabius</hi> reflected, his credit was great, his foot muſt not ſtirre, but the whole earth muſt ſhiver: his head muſt not move, but the very heavens muſt tremble: when hee rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177091:25"/> the whole univerſe muſt quake in a dreadful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: therefore <hi>Fabius</hi> bids his courage be quiet, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſuch time as an opportunitie falls out, hee may doe ſomething becomming a <hi>Maximus.</hi> Say you ſo too, when you are challenged by a boyſterous quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reller, that you hold him no fit matter for your cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to worke upon; and ſo ſhew that you can take time to deliberate, what a man of your rights to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is fitting ſhould doe.</p>
               <p>Old Souldiers, (that ever be the valianteſt men) will ſticke long before you can get their heads into a quarrell: they know what obligations follow men that goe to the field, what ties of honour doe gird their great hearts. When a valiant man is bent upon revenge, hee will take it: hee muſt not play the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cocke, if the thunder-bolt ſtrike, it muſt turne the bardeſt metall into duſt: and ſtout mens anger muſt not be the puſh of a feather, blowne off with a faire word, with a little entreatie. The valiant man reflects what a great opinion of valour, the world holds on him: a verie ſweet &amp; pleaſing thing to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but chargeable in its retinue; when wrongs do cal it abroad, it muſt have a great traine of bloud after it, to amaze an Injurer. The ſtout man conſidereth the great report there is of the excellencie of metall within him: and therefore now that it is to come forth, if it doe not carrie away the eyes of all men, he ſhall be a ſcorne for ever: his honour hath beene yet amongſt his neighbours, but as the bloſſome on a tree, or corne in the buske; now time is come that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177091:26"/> all men will expect a harveſt, the ſickle muſt goe, and everie body will be gaping at what is reaped; wide gaping wounds muſt be the barnes, where hee muſt inne his honour. With theſe and like reflections, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage doth hang its courſe almoſt ſtill in the deepeſt reſentments; and certainly, whil'ſt quarrellers, like little brookes, keepe a loud prattling, manhood glides ſo quiet, that you would thinke it is not moved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fabius Maximus</hi> commanded his courage to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare <hi>Hannibal,</hi> expecting for his valour ſome better ſervice, to preſent it to his Countrey; it was not feare of death, that frighted him. So you ſhall ſee; let Rome, in whoſe hands hee willingly leaves the raines of his valour, ſet him aworke with three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men onely, hee will ſet upon all the warlike troopes of <hi>Hannibal.</hi> The neceſſitie of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, bids the Romane Eagles flie, a <hi>Fabius</hi> ſhall flie before them: and all the beames of <hi>Hannibals</hi> gliſtring Armie, ſhall not dazle the eyes of <hi>Fabius:</hi> But he ſhall pull the rayes from <hi>Hannibals</hi> head, and ſtrike therehence his frontlet: and ſo like a Phoenix of Honour, dye amid the beames of the African glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: having the frontlet about him.</p>
               <p>Certainly, men may ſtay from fighting, and yet have a great minde to fight; when a good occaſion is wanting, it is wiſdome, to locke up your valour, fortunate be they that can doe it. When you are too weake, to goe into the bluſtringaire, you keepe your chamber; that is not to keep your houſe, but to keep your health: ſo to ſtay out of the way, is not alwayes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177091:26"/> ſervile feare, ſometimes it is ſtrength of courage, that expects hard for a victorie. The Souldier that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermineth the wall, you will not ſay, he hideth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe blindly in a wonty-locke; hee walketh but a while in a hole, to raiſe up his valour with a brighter glorie. So when men ſtay from fighting, if a chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge be given, and no anſwer had, let it not be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med cowardlineſſe; it may be manhood is labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with its full ſtrength, to reach the furtheſt pitch of valour, it is not to run away, but to fetch a fee to leape beyond the Worthies. Actions of conſequence, as honour is, required good deliberation: we ſee ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie often times, men wiſh themſelves againe at the the beginning of a quarrell, whereunto they have fallen too too ſuddenly: therefore the beſt Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are ſlow fighters, and it will be a long time before hot words can heat them: the fuell that makes the ſtrongeſt fire, you take it tardie a kindling, whiles light ſtraw will ſoone preſent your eye with flaſhes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="point">
               <head>Point. 3.</head>
               <head type="sub">Suffer. 3. <hi>True valour reſerveth it ſelfe, for weightier imployments, than to dance in a Duell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAve you true courage? the marke will not be, that you rore booted and ſpurred for a Duell: when valour is in you, you will hang out for your ſigne, <hi>Silence.</hi> A man that layes up gold
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177091:27"/> in heapes, lieth; ſpends not on Ladies ſmiles, ſugar ſuppers: nor turnes his money to ſmoake in a Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin: and who owneth the treaſure of valour, ſhuts it up better than to vapour it out, to draw it forth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on everie Mad-caps frowne to a killing: When af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts call men of courage abroad, their valour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites them to ſtay at home: it is gentile, and muſt not goe into ill company. Great valours have alwayes great fortunes to follow, and no leiſure to attend quarrellers: therefore when private wrongs doe flie, the valiant mans eye doth not regard them.</p>
               <p>The Romane Orator leading a ſtreame of elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to overflow the merits of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> preſenteth us with his pietie in war, his courage in peace, his ſtaid heart in victories, and his riſing hopes in miſ-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes: One fault <hi>Cicero</hi> confeſſeth in him, that hee had no memorie. And was <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſo forgetfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed? I am ſure he forgot himſelfe leſſe than all the Romane Captaines that went before him; for quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he tooke up the Diadem from under a company of Gulls or Conſulls, that ſo long bred it amongſt them, and never ſpied it. But yet (ſaith <hi>Cicero) Caeſar</hi> was forgetfull, of what? <hi>Extollens dicebat Cicero,</hi> ſaith the learned African, mee thinkes I ſee <hi>Cicero</hi> breake out into a ſmile, and ſay, <hi>Nihil obliviſci ſolebat niſi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurias:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apud Aug. Epiſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 5. <hi>ad Marcall.</hi>
                  </note> Valiant <hi>Caeſar</hi> could not frame himſelfe to picke ſtrawes, or picke quarrells, (which is all one) he could never beſtow ſo ill his courage; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you would thinke ever he did forget his injurer: his private abuſes, hee laid ſo far out of minde, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177091:27"/> time would ſay, he could never remember them. It ſeemes hee kept all the roomes of his thoughts for conqueſts: for everie corner of his heart, he had a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Kingdome: therefore hee would make no place for ſhuffling quarrells: no, it was a furtherance to his victories, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> had a ſpeciall gift, in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no gift at all of memorie, for his wrongs: and ſo <hi>Cicero</hi> goeth on neatly, obſerving <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who was of ſo excellent a memorie, ſo rare in that Art, that hee was not knowne ever to have forgotten any thing: <hi>Nihil obliviſci ſolebat:</hi> yet, to everie man hee did ſeeme mainely forgetfull of his injuries, hee did ſo wonderfully ſleepe in them: and it was, he would not ſtirre in them, hee had ſo much other worke for his courage.</p>
               <p>Had not the ſingular valour of <hi>Caeſar</hi> done ſo, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> yet <hi>Cicero</hi> did moſt well to ſay ſo: becauſe great <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſhould have done ſo: and not onely all the great maſters of the earth, but alſo everie man of manhood: valour ſhould follow glorie, not hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: ſo neat a thing as valour is, ſhould be ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on better worke, than to cobble up Duells: <hi>Dicebat adulator,</hi> did <hi>Cicero</hi> but complement with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> yet truly <hi>Talem eſſe debere oſtendebat Principem civitatis</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>qualem illum (Caeſarem) praedicabat: Cicero</hi> wiſely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed what was fitting for great courages to doe; men that will be great, muſt keepe their ſtomackes to hard meat; it muſt not be ſaid of them, they can ſwallow nothing but milke ſops: You muſt learne to diſgeſt great quarrells, you muſt have the ſtomack
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177091:28"/> of an Oſtrich, ſometimes to ſwallow iron: though one draw on you, and wound you, yet a more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious imployment, muſt hold your courage, from laying your heart upon the revenge of it: valiant men muſt not admit, that everie little crum of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content can choake them: no, valour muſt ſwallow better than ſo: elſe the world, that ſo ſwarmeth with diſpleaſing ſucceſſes, had never made, of valorous men, its victors. Hence it came, that when <hi>Marke Antonie</hi> quarrelled with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> yet <hi>Caeſar</hi> would not awake, hee was ſo ſleepie, that his legs could not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie him to the field, as I ſaid before.</p>
               <p>This great <hi>Auguſtus</hi> was a Prince, got well by his weapon, therfore he had no reaſon to refuſe to uſe it; and the edge of his courage was well ſteeled with skill, therefore there was no great cauſe for him to feare <hi>Marke Antonie</hi> his arme, that was but a pillow for Ladies to lye on. This <hi>Caeſar</hi> is the verie ſame (though others ſay it was <hi>Iulius Caeſar)</hi> that comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the timorſome Boat-man, with a <hi>Caeſarem vehis:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Flerus.</note> aſſuring him, rough miſ-fortunes durſt not appeare in the preſence of <hi>Caeſar:</hi> why then ſhould <hi>Caeſar</hi> feare an effeminate <hi>Antonie?</hi> ſurely it could not be feare, it was love, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> bore to his valour. He reſolved to reſerve the thing he loved ſo deare, for more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious actions: he would not ſpend of it, with that Spend-thrift of honour, <hi>Marke Antonie:</hi> hee played the better husband, and kept good metall for good uſe.</p>
               <p>So, when the perfumed Courtier <hi>Antony</hi> challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177091:28"/> 
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> to fight in ſingle combat, <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaith to him in ſadneſſe hee will not: doth <hi>Caeſar</hi> therefore not love fighting? not ſo, <hi>Caeſar</hi> rather loved it ſo well, that he will not beſtow it upon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Aegyptian: <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> prizeth fighting higher, than to caſt away, as much as one craſh, on a coward: <hi>Caeſars</hi> fights, are to winne kingdomes, not to winne conceits: a <hi>Caeſar</hi> will not ſpend his blowes to beat off cocks-combs, but to ſtrike downe crownes: weightie muſt be the occaſion, that can make ſtout men ſtirre: children may run after ſhittle cockes.</p>
               <p>So you men of worth, you ſhould ſet more by your lims, then to lay them at the ſtake to any that will play againſt them: ſhall every coward cut the cards upon you? call you at all times of the night of darke paſſion, and ſhall he ſo trample your life, that is the fruitfull bed of honour, wherein ſo many glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions grow, in peace and in warre? will you hazard all, of a challenger will draw cuts for it: if hee will cut off your necke, will you carry it to the field as quickely, as for your Prince to the ſcaffold? ſee what ſoveraigntie you give unto baſe quarrellers. This is to make Apes leaders of Lyons: with lives men of great credit, ſhould not part ſo eaſily: our jewels ſometimes we looſe, yet we find them againe; but our lives once gone, we never meet them more, till the great wake of <hi>Ioſaphat:</hi> therefore, you valiant men, ſeeing you gaine ſo much by life, you ſhould have more care to keepe life on foot: all ſparkling ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, all glittering valour, life is the cabonet that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177091:29"/> keepes it: hacke life to peeces, what remaines, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vergain you honour: it is but a lumpe of ſenſleſſe fleſh, ſo cowardly, that abuſe it then, caſt it on the ground, it dares not ſtirre: affront a body then, ſee if it dare challenge, it dare do nothing but grinne, and looke pale: wherefore if you love valour ſo well for honours ſake; love life a little better, and keepe it, to get you more honour, caſt not life away ſo ſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>But doe you in honour burſt with a Phanaticke deſire, the world ſhould know, that in your heart doth grow the orient pearle of valour; and I pray you, what is it? forſooth, that you can carry thorow your hot heart, a piece of cold yron and ſmile at it: that death never brings unto you her dreadfulneſſe: why if you be ſo hot, walke alone to the warre, and ſhew ſo much there: doe ſervice to your moſt wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerving king therewith, who will regard your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement by pay; ſo, your valour, unto honor, you ſhal adde profit, and by this, you may riſe further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to honour. Creepe not up and downe a countrey, killing rotten ſheepe, poore ſilly fellowes, that when you bore them, you looſe more ale than bloud out of their bodies. If you will ſtrike like a mightie one, ſtrike at the mountaines of manhood, ſet at ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: if you have fire, burne high Cedars, let low ſhrubs alone for little ones to blaze on: the high region of a thundering aire ſends its boults againſt the higheſt towres, it ſets againſt what ſtands migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt; but you muſt take in hand what lieth neareſt:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177091:29"/> aſſoone as a neighbour angreth you, then you muſt needs fight: good Lord, how ſoone your valour ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth at home: if your courage be ſo earely up, why doe you not ſend it abroad to the field breath it up a rampier, where it ſhal finde worke enough? But your worke muſt bee by the fire ſide, you muſt fight at home, that is your goodly valour. I muſt tell you, ſuch men be alwaies of the chilleſt courage: and I beleeve though they now glow in London, they will quickly have a cold fit at the newes of a Canon: I wiſh them to take Phyſicke, and from Saint <hi>George</hi> his field, to lead their courage under Saint <hi>George</hi> his banner: it will turne their ſtomacke, and cure their choller.</p>
               <p>That famous <hi>Bachet,</hi> luſtre of the Eaſt, and <note place="margin">Holy court.</note> Generall of the Turkiſh Armies, underſtanding one of his Captaines had challenged his fellow ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier; and both were gone to field, to coole their cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler with cold ſteele: <hi>Bachet</hi> broke out into a moſt feeling compaſſion. O, quoth he! what is our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? ſhall we kill no more enemies, have wee done with the Iewiſh Redeemers children (that deſerve not the names of men) ſhal no more of them ſcrawle on the tops of our launces? In a world of hatefull adverſaries, can wee finde leiſure thus to turne our weapons upon the hearts of our fellowes? have wee no more greatneſſe to offer unto <hi>Mahomets</hi> glorie, that thus wee hang up our weapons in the boſomes of the ſupporters of his temple? O, Engliſh Duel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, this Turke remembers you of a noble leſſon: if
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177091:30"/> your choller boyles ſo faſt about your heart, that it makes your fingers ends tingle: lay them not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon your neighbours, your kings ſubiects; but go further from home, to prey upon humane bloud: your king hath enemies in the world, fal you on them abroad, and the kings lawes will in requital fal upon your foes at home. When your King hath no ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, yet you may finde your ſelfe warre-like worke: bring in new found lands, to in large your kings kingdomes: the greatneſſe of his royall merits de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve roome to ſpread over far more large territories: the Ocean ſhould burſt with ſhame to preſſe meares unto his Empire: rather it ſhould open its boſome, and give ground to lay unto his Dominions: and go to overflow with its waves the countries of leſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Princes: not bite away one crowne from the Brittaine ſhores; great <hi>Charles</hi> his glorie hath need of every ſand, to reckon his ſingular merits.</p>
               <p>Walke you Dueller with your valour, abroad the world, it hath a large ſcope, and many skirts; finde you one to lye upon, &amp; lay on in a iuſt conqueſt lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily: ſhew greatneſſe of valour in that you can make your good king greater; and waſte not his ſubiects at home, ſo you make him leſſer: to ſhew your fiery mettle conſume not your kings power. If you have skill to kill, open your ſhop where that trade will bee in good liking: if all your labor is to make the world know you care not for death; walke there where you ſhall ſee it wait at your heeles; and cryes round about you every minute, bring you tidings, it wil be anone
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177091:30"/> within you. <hi>Bachet</hi> was a great ſouldier, of ſtout courage, and though bloudy enough (hee was a Turke) yet hee miſliked mightily challenges and privat combats: hee deemed them but a havocke of manhood. If wee will needs play at kill-game, let us not play like boyes, that muſt alwaies play neere their owne doores; let us goe where there is want of killers: at home there wants good livers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="point">
               <head>Point 4.</head>
               <head type="sub">Suffer. 4. <hi>The valorous man his greateſt victorie is to overcome himſelfe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt will you live at home, and fight too, and come by a mightie opinion of valour: I will deſcry unto you neere your owne doores, <hi>a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raincognita</hi> (your ſelfe <hi>noſce teipſum)</hi> a whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to winne, <hi>A microcoſmos,</hi> a little world, ful of great Commanders and fierce enemies, to conquer. I will carry you before two great high towers, of two mightie powers: the one, you will finde ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to maſter you, that it is all knowledge, the other ſo wilfull to croſſe you, that it is nothing but will: ſo ſtrange, that all the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of heaven and earth never makes it doe, but its owne will. <hi>I</hi> will lead you amongſt the ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of ſenſuall pleaſures; and ſhew you the ſtrong hold of delight: the induſtrious ſleights of profit: the wearileſſe toyle of gaine: the wonderfull confidence
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177091:31"/> of eaſe. Muſter up here your couragiouſeſt reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, you ſhal march amongſt a number of moſt cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning foes: doe you know where the moſt potent lord <hi>Selfe</hi> raigneth? one ſo ambitious, that the whole face of the earth hath bin ever yet too narrow for him to lay his eye upon; he rowles it into the bottom of the ſeas, unto the centre of the earth, and crieth out ſtill for more roome. One ſo mightily troubleſome that he pillageth all the fields of Nature with whole armies of unſatiable Paſſions, that ſwell againſt the very heavens; that ſtrike at the very face of him that holds his head higher than the ſtarres. One ſo vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in his very heart, that after he is utterly defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and laied on the ground, ſevered in pieces like a Snake, yet the one part of him will ſtir, and keep ſuch a ſtirre, that it will raile and revile againſt its Victor, for a whole eternitie.</p>
               <p>Do you deſire not to go farre, and yet to go a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating? why, take this combat in hand; ſet at this ſtrong enemie, and trie your valor on him: he dwels neare enough unto you, you may bee quickely with him, he is your owne ſelfe. I ſay, if you deſire to take a maſter-peece of worke in hand, maſter your ſelfe; and one thing know for your comfort, if you can compaſſe it, the noyſe of your worthineſſe ſhall ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe all the nine of the fame. For who overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth himſelfe, may challenge the freedome to take the firſt place amongſt the valiant. Call you in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <hi>Caeſar</hi> to a firſt chaire: him, ſo univerſall a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, that the Princes of the earth preſented him
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177091:31"/> with Scepters, as meane tenants do their Land-lords with Chickins: you think this old ſouldier becomes the chaire well: you ſhall ſee a young <hi>Cato,</hi> a conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of himſelfe, come in and bid him riſe, &amp; will take place of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cato</hi> the yonger, at the time the Roman glorie was <note place="margin">The French A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademy of Pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re de Priman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note> clouded in the ſad ſiege of Vtica, was moved by his fellow Romans, lying al cloſe blocked up, to ſubmit unto conquering <hi>Caeſar,</hi> elſe all muſt die. Valiant <hi>Cato</hi> at the mention of death, reades the inventorie of all his goods or goodneſſes of all his life; hee hath a long rowle of many good morall vertues: under the head of his conqueſts, he runnes over a number of great price: but under the head of his ſelfe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts he findes a great ſtore: it ſeemes it was uſuall with him to overcome himſelfe. Hee often had cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed his anger, riſing againſt ſome great men of the Citie, which might have driven him into rebellion. Hee had maſtered his ambition, which perchance would haveled him upon the ſame action, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> now is, to command the gates of Rome: but <hi>Cato</hi> bridled his unruly paſſions, better. <hi>Cato</hi> therefore anſwereth, hee will not ſubmit unto <hi>Caeſar.</hi> I (ſayth <hi>Cato)</hi> have trulier conquered than <hi>Caeſar;</hi> therefore <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould rather ſubmit unto me. <hi>Caeſar</hi> hee is now taken and overcome: therefore none can make ſubmiſſion unto him as conquerour. <hi>Caeſar,</hi> his own vitious ambition to maſter all, hath caſt him over us all. His great feare (having offended ſome of the Senate) hath bound him faſt to the Scepter to fence
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177091:32"/> himſelfe withall: for, could <hi>Caeſar</hi> have ſubmitted his fierce diſpoſition to the grave Lawes of the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, which doubtleſſe would have had a worthy fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of him; their owne profit by his conqueſts, would have ſweetned their trouble in the rugged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his nature: for wiſe men know a great ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit cannot ſerve them, but it muſt ſometime offend them; and actions from humane fleſh, we muſt bee contented to take them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as fiſh, a good one, and a ſhrow: could <hi>Caeſar</hi> but have beene a little tractable to the light of higher powers, his heart had never va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poured ſo much heavy griefe as would preſume to cloud the lawes of Rome, and for ever to eclipſe the government of ſo many hundred yeares ſhining: u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping over the Senat ſoveraigne power himſelfe, who by right of cradle, deſerved not to be their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt fellow. Therefore <hi>Cato</hi> ſtil ſaith, he will account himſelfe the invincible, becauſe in maſtering of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he is mightier than <hi>Caeſar. Cato</hi> ſcorned to yeeld unto the Victor of Rome: breathing the glory of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Victor over himſelfe.</p>
               <p>We are now come to the hold and keep, who muſt be the better man, he that can quarrell, or he that can ſuffer; who maſtereth many others, or who ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe. Wee dare goe over ſhooes in bloud to angle for honour, but wee know not whether to goe from home with <hi>Caeſar</hi> amongſt ſtrangers, or home againe with <hi>Cato</hi> unto ourſelves. An offence is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and you reſolve therefore you muſt overcome your enemy, why doe you not reſolve, you muſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177091:32"/> overcome your ſelfe? you ſay you muſt fight, why ſay you not, you muſt be quiet: How doe you prove, that it becomes a valiant man better to fight, than to ſuffer? Or how is it a leſſer victorie to conquer ones ſelfe, than another? You plead you muſt diſcover valour, I ſay ſo to, but let us finde the beſt way: it will ever fall out, that we ſhal ſtill come home againe to your ſelfe, and within your ſelfe, wee ſhall finde the beſt matter of victories. It is a golden verſe of a good Poet, repeated by moſt Writers; it ſeemes the witty ſaying doth take many:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fortior eſt qui ſe, quàm qui fortiſsima vincit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <note place="margin">Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uanu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Moenia: nec virtus, altior ire poteſt.</l>
                  <l>Arduares, viciſſe alios, victoria major,</l>
                  <l>Eſt animi motus, compoſuiſſe ſui.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O'recome your ſelf, thats more than towres of braſſe</l>
                  <l>To win, your vertue can no higher paſſe.</l>
                  <l>Hard thing it is, ſtrong Armies to confound;</l>
                  <l>But more to hold your raging paſſions bound.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Sentence is given: it is more to beat ones <hi>Selfe,</hi> than a many thouſands: therefore if you run a duel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, onely out of a deſire to get honour: lay chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges with others aſide, and make it your quarrell to maſter your ſelfe: chuſe it, as the moſt difficult Duell, to overcome your ſelfe.</p>
               <p>The nearer an enemie layeth ſiege to a Citie, the more valour it is, to beat him backe; and what can be more neare you, then what is within you. <hi>Magis ſunt</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:177091:33"/> 
                  <hi>periculoſa quae domeſtica,</hi> as <hi>Lactantius,</hi> very wittily <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>inſt. cap.</hi> 9.</note> obſerveth. A civill warre is the foreſt blow to a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: becauſe each part is ſure to weaken the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and all parts growing weake, that body muſt needs die. Yet there, onely one part is againſt the other; but here all againſt everie part of you; you rob your hands of their labours, your underſtanding you bereave o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght; from your will you ſteale its good cuſtomes: and from your internall ſenſes, their gentle inclinations to right; and thus you whoſe greatneſſe conſiſts of many Powers, doe engage your whole ſelfe in undoing everie ſeverall part of your owne ſtrength: then here is a civill warre more dangerous: When two Combators have loſt the wales of their weapons, and cannot keepe one another out any longer, when fencing can maintaine no diſtance betweene them, but they are come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one anothers armes, then begins the bloudie part of the combat, there is nothing but poaching at life, ſtrikes everie blow as faſt as the weapon can come and goe. Can any be more within you, than your owne ſelfe? none doth lay at you more fiercely. Then this is the moſt dangerous Duell. You ſhall not gape to eat, but the enemie creepes in at your mouth, and turnes your full ſtomack, to deſire what is not, to torture you. You ſhall not goe to bed, but he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes you betweene ſheets, and ſets difficult fancies on you, and keepes your eyes open in ſpite of the rod of <hi>Mercurie:</hi> if toyle caſt you into a little ſleepe, the enemie watcheth your firſt waking, hee falleth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177091:33"/> to the ſame game againe, and peſtereth you with moſt heat, when you be moſt naked. Riſe, and hee will make you ſow teares in vaine, reape words with no gaine: and betweene wind and water he will hit you ſo ſore, that it is a thouſand to one, he will ſinke you. Is it not therefore good reaſon, that the ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his enemie, (ones <hi>Selfe)</hi> ſhould be judged the greateſt conqueſt.</p>
               <p>This enemie doth fight upon ſuch advantages, that it muſt needs be your greateſt glorie to conquer him. And hence you ſhall ever finde thoſe your beſt victories, whereof ſome part is, to overcome your ſelfe. A golden conſequence! if to conquer, you muſt maſter your ſelfe, your victories be profitable: the more they have of ſelfe-maſterſhip, the more they will have of profit: for by our difficulties &amp; diſlikes, we know what doth become us: and by our deſires, we reckon ſtill our miſtakings: I will talke ſtill of things within the compaſſe of courage.</p>
               <p>You are right valiant, as light to fight as a feather. Why there be peeviſh oppoſing Spirits abroad in your pariſh, that men cannot dwell by with quiet: if you durſt but touch them with a word, they would like a Betle leave their filthy burthen of malice: and you finde great difficultie to ſpeake, you ſweat and groane with the conceit that a word muſt come out of your mouth, you are in labour. Overcome your ſelfe here, chuſe this combat, and let Challengers alone. More, I will chuſe you another combat. Your ſervants, within your owne doores, dare be diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:177091:34"/> your Officers over-careleſſe, or over-covetous, or both: if you have a ſtomacke that can riſe, ſet againſt theſe. O you will not endure the toyle, you cannot ſuffer the barking noiſe of your own diſorders, you will never abide to heare again of your own foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh expences, to offer you notes is to caſt motes in your eyes, you finde mightie trouble. Why, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come your ſelfe, you ſhall ſee it one of your beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts: be not a coward, runne not away from your ſelfe, maſter your ſelfe for ſhame, to be maſter of your owne: ſure, you are ſo great, ſo honourable, that you are afraid of your ſelfe: ſubdue your ſelfe in moſt things, ſo your ſpoyles ſhall be the heapes of many happineſſes.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>—Tunc omnia jure tenebis,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Claud. ad Theod. Imp.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cum poteris rex eſſe tui.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Will you put all conqueſts into one, conquer your ſelfe: who cannot doe ſo, will never be Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of valour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hercules,</hi> you thinke, was a tall man, and had good ſtrength: that could teare Lyons, beare on his backe whole miskins, over-run horſes, over-flie birds, and roule up and downe the world doing wonders: Surely he had great limbs, yet <hi>Lactantius</hi> noted, they wanted their beſt ſinewes: <hi>Vellem adje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſet</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lact. ut ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>de inſolentia:</hi> I wiſh I could heare of ſome feats of <hi>Hercules,</hi> how he dealt with his enemies at home: you tell me hee did beat monſters, but durſt he touch
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:177091:34"/> himſelfe: I heare he did cleanſe neighbours dung-hills, but was hee not apt to crow upon his owne dung-hill? <hi>Vellem adjeciſſet de inſolentia:</hi> I feare hee was a little inſolent. I ſhould be glad to heare ſome newes, how he maſtered his owne minde: and then ſaith <hi>Lactantius,</hi> I will yeeld unto antiquitie, and confeſſe that <hi>Hercules</hi> was a valiant man indeed, and a mirror of valour. Otherwiſe I will ſay, <hi>Hercules</hi> deſerveth not his name, under the fame as it goeth. For I will no more eſteeme him, for conquering beaſts, birds, and enemies, than I will eſteeme of a childe treading upon ſo many little Ants. <hi>Animum vincere fortiſsimum eſt,</hi> It is the conqueſt of himſelfe that muſt make <hi>Hercules</hi> famous.</p>
               <p>If you be ambitious of glorie, here is a way for you to goe beyond <hi>Hercules: Non enim fortior eſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candus, qui leonem, quàm qui iracundiam in ſe inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lact. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>ſuperat.</hi> When your heart doth fill with filthy revenge, ſweeten it with mercie, and you ſhall bee <hi>Hercules,</hi> not the other fellow for cleanſing the Kings ſtables: when your angrie thoughts flie unto the Higher Powers for puniſhment againſt your enemie; flie you to overtake thoſe thoughts, and tell them there is a God in Heaven, that bids you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give: ſo you ſhall be the true <hi>Hercules,</hi> and not hee that overtooke a bird with an arrow. If the light of reaſon might be ſuffered to prefer a ray in the Star-Chamber; it would moſt humbly deſire reflection upon the riots againſt reaſon, wherein by violence of weapons ſuch ſtrange value of valour is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177091:35"/> ſuch unlawfull meaſures of honour are ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with bloud. One that can but force a Beare, or face a Bull, is cried for valiant; and he that doth the wonder of wonders, who maſtereth himſelfe, is jee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for a Coward. Let one overcome himſelfe, hee muſt out-run his Countrey; all men will ſo point at him for a meere Noddie, as fit for nothing but to make a Lubber, to lye in a Monaſterie; whiles per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, for a worthy effuſion of bloud he hath a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter courage, than you that doe but play the Scullion, running up and downe the field to ſticke a Gooſe. I admire not that vice is in good liking, it doth unto moſt men a pleaſure: but when men without bluſh doe praiſe vice, I feare their faith hath a tainture. It may be a wonder in future ages that men deſired to doe well, and ſaid they durſt not, for feare of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the vulgar; they acknowledged they did ill, and could do no otherwiſe, they muſt be ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled by the coyiſh fancie of the Commons.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:177091:35"/>
            <head>Section III. <hi>Seven Antidotes, or quicke Reaſons to put off Quarrells.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Take not notice of everie wrong.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>You are not the worſe for a diſcourteſie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Put off wrongs with ſome pleaſant jeſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>In baſe occaſions ſuffer wrongs to puniſh yeur ſelfe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>Beare with friends, be quiet and you puniſh your foes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>Revenge not wrongs ſuddenly.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>Will nothing doe good? Remember the tree at the Townes end.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſeaſes of Duelliſme have ſo long ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in our Kingdome: our over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great hearts ſwell ſo quickly with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of cruell revenge, that to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a cure, is but to waſh an Aethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ope: there is difference indeed in colour, as between the jet and the ſcarlet: but colour in graine hardly admits a change, and Quarrellers are in graine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly. The nature of this burning feaver, is to ſtrike to the heart, which in an heape of reſentments, not well digeſted, falleth into ſuch an Apoplexie, that it findeth eaſe in nothing, but in bleeding. And though
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177091:36"/> a combat be but one to one, it is an hundred to one both dye of it.</p>
            <p>To come now and profeſſe cures, for all ſuch as roare under theſe dangerous purples, were but to act a Mountebanke, which if hee can but make names for ſome few ſalves, it ſufficeth for his gaines: hee takes mens monies, and for mens cures he cares not: theſe muſt ever beare an after-date, untill ſuch time as he ſhall be abſent from place and ſhame, and then it never troubleth him that never returneth. I ſhould be glad, if of a few that read my receipts, I could eaſe any; many be the occaſions of Duells, divers the diſpoſitions of men that move them, and unto man and matter the Antidote ſhould fit, elſe it will but trouble the eye, and enter no further: yet I muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to give, and you Reader, perchance to ſeeke, and to finde nothing.</p>
            <div n="1" type="point">
               <head>Point. 1.</head>
               <head type="sub">Antidote. 1. <hi>Take not notice of everie wrong, you will otherwiſe but vex your ſelfe, without need.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOme men will feed upon poyſon, and certainly ſome ſtomacks relliſh nothing but wrangling: the world worketh now adayes a ſtrange kinde of medley, of cunning and folly: ſome forget them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves mightily, they will ſleepe drunke in everie tap-houſe, and yet they will watch; they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177091:36"/> a ſhrewd turn a neighbour doth them, from the cradle to the grave. They will finde ſuch gaps to creepe into quarrellings; through a hedge they wil follow a pig: through a hole of a cott, they will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a calfe for a ſtraw: they will turne bloud-hound and tract a childe for a ſticke; a man for treading a graſſe that doth but peep out of a path: and all this induſtrie onely to finde themſelves brabbles. <hi>O quam ſolers eſt iracundia ad fingendas cauſas furoris!</hi> I admire ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> the cunning that froward men have to frame combuſtions of nothing.</p>
               <p>If Law will not ſerve quick, as their peeviſh mind doth call; if paper bils cannot hurt, they will put in ſharper weapons; the ſteele, the piſtoll ſhall cocke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad: and thus in a peaceable kingdom, we live (as it were) on the frontiers of a mercileſſe enemie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> now you ſee cattell driven, now violent hands laid on men, and they ſo handled, that it mattereth not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be drawne to an averſe king, or a dread full dungeon: for ſlavery is the end of both Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes.</p>
               <p>The ſubtleneſſe that ſome men uſe (though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſimple) to tricke up a quarrel, and to ſet it forth, meriteth obſervation. What a quicke eye to note it? what a curious eare to take it up, amongſt a noiſe of by-matters? Some have the ſleight of raking ſparkes of diſcontents together, and keeping them long hot under the aſhes of a counterfeit correſpondency; ſo at their pleaſure they will ſteale an opportunity, to ſet all a Countrey together by the eares.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:177091:37"/>
               <p> Certainely, ſuch conditions are of the nature of Witches, that lie alwaies in ambuſh to do miſchiefe: they live the life of a cut-purſe, whoſe necke is neereſt the halter, when his hand gets neereſt the treaſure: ſo theſe, when they bee fulleſt of matter of quarrels, (which they greedily gape after) then they bee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt from their owne quietneſſe.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, wiſemen will rather beſtow their wits in taking upon them ſomtimes, not to ſee what their owne eies doth ſhew them. Doe any affronts ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, by word or deed againſt you? ſtill the occaſion, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blow nor breath, be neither hot nor cold; carry your ſelfe ſo, that the ſtanders by ſhall not perceive you do heare it. So they may come almoſt to thinke it was not you that was injured, they will rather draw in ſome other: that is an excellent skill. Hereby you ſhall keepe your valours credit, freeing it from ingagements for your honour; and you may have your ful ſtrength to put upon actions more for your profit, to tug in matters that may rather increaſe ſtrength than draw bloud from you.</p>
               <p>Turne therefore a quarrell off with ſome pretty queſtion, or ſudden diſcourſe to a ſtander by: draw your ſpirits ſo haſtily another way, that your bloud ſhall not have leiſure to riſe into diſorder: diſtract the hearers with an unexpected event: with draw your ſenſes, faſten upon ſome obiect, cloaſe choler that would ſtirre: round mens eares with new reflections, turne them into cares: nip a diſcourſe, giddy it, that it may not turne directly unto you againe: break off
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:177091:37"/> companie, upon pretence of a weighty buſineſſe, and then let none bring you thither againe. Let the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronter put on never ſo openly; an undaunted ſpirit will deceive him of his marke, and put him out of his aime.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cato,</hi> that worthy Romane, in a bathe was bare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Senec. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de ira.</hi>
                  </note> a ſawcy fellow taunted him, and gave him a box on the eare; yet <hi>Cato</hi> tooke no notice of it; <hi>Cato</hi> ſaid nothing. What could be a more publick wrong; and in the bathe, wee heare no newes of it, no char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Conſtables with the villaine that ſtrooke <hi>Cato.</hi> All is in a huſh: ſure <hi>Cato</hi> was not ſtrucken: yes, <hi>Catonem</hi> (indeed) <hi>quidam percuſſit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> but <hi>Cato</hi> would take no notice of it, <hi>maluit non agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No queſtion but <hi>Cato</hi> did feele the ſmart: yet his excellent wit found way to put ſhame by: doubtleſſe his eare did glow, but his heart would not ſhew it. The man that ſtrook felt <hi>Cato</hi> ſo ſtedfaſt, that having given the blow, hee thought almoſt that he was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, and had not hit <hi>Cato</hi> at all; rather that <hi>Cato</hi> was not there, either was gone in an extaſie, into ſome region of Nature, profoundly ſearching out curioſities: or into the Schoole of the Stoicks pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring maxims to bridle humane paſſions, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was not there when the blow was ſtrooken at him; it was but the ſhadow of <hi>Cato,</hi> or a bunch of ſtones, or hard bones that was ſmitten, as if one had ſtrooke but the houſe for the owner. See how this ſtriker hath loſt his marke, and hath done nothing:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:177091:38"/> hee aimed to affront <hi>Cato,</hi> but could not, becauſe <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> could then not bee with his body, to the others thinking. So <hi>Cato</hi> ſaved himſelfe from diſgrace by his wiſe deportment, and rightly ſaid, <hi>Maluit non ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere, quàm ignoſcere.</hi> It was to bee expected from <hi>Cato</hi> that he ſhould ſo do, he muſt not ſay, an affront did pierce him that hee was hurt: abuſes muſt paſſe by him, as waves by a rocke, that never reckoneth them. It is a better teſtimonie of ones greatneſſe, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to have had a foe, than to have revenged or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given him (which is the revenge of a <hi>Cato)</hi> for if you forgive, you confeſſe you were wronged, and that is a weakneſſe; therefore <hi>Maluit non agnoſcere, quàm ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere:</hi> a Ruffian may ſtrike a <hi>Cato;</hi> but yet <hi>Cato</hi> wil ſay he was not touched; ſo will you become a great ſpirit, a <hi>Cato:</hi> take no notice, feele not weak ones, they may do wrong to you, &amp; harm themſelves, but never hurt you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="point">
               <head>Point. 2.</head>
               <head type="sub">Antidote 2. <hi>You are not the worſe for a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courteſie. Then buſie not your ſelfe with nothing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COnſider with your ſelfe, what are you the worſe, for the neglect full word or act of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? you uſe to ſay, words breake no bones; why then will you breake your heart to be revenged
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177091:38"/> of them? your enemie ſpake unto you a word, and perchance but a word, and is your choler ſo quicke, that therefore you will to blowes with him? You ſay, he touched you in your honour, what then? hee did but touch you, and will a touch hurt you? men that wil be eſteemed of valor, ſaith <hi>Gonſalvo,</hi> ſhould <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verulam de irae num.</hi> 57.</note> have <hi>telam honoris craſſiorem:</hi> is your honor ſo thin skinned, that a puſh with a ruſh will teare it? is there no honour of Musket proofe? ſhall every beardleſſe boy with a croſſe-bow that can ſcarce ſcarre a Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, aſtoniſh you? ſtill your ſelfe rather a little, with a reflection, an acknowledgement of your owne cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: cry not out, one pinch hath undone you: hold a while rather than confeſſe your honour to bee of ſuch an over-delicat temper: what hurt can the touch of a word doe? can a little diſreſpect wound, which hits onely by conceit, and is nothing but <hi>ens rationis?</hi> We have an old countrey man of our owne, which our new ones might imitate with credit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperour, his picture was drawne with a ſingular repreſentation of great Maieſtie: ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſt. hom.</hi> 20. <hi>ad pop. Antioch. Garo. to.</hi> 3. <hi>ad An. Dom.</hi> 324</note> with Crownes, and ſtrewed under feet with ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as ruſhes: beames rounded it with glory, and embroydered curtaines on rods of gold did defie the motes that dare ſet at the raies of the Sunne from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing that Picture: all this ambition of reverence as an expreſſion of a more veneration unto the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours perſon, freed not this Picture from a diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full affront. A moſt idle fellow, found an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie to caſt filth on it.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:177091:39"/>
               <p> See now <hi>Conſtantine</hi> with his beams and bravery, all to beſmeared with durt by a moſt baſe creature: the mightie Emperour of the world is laied in the mire, thinke you him not mightily diſpleaſed? can you imagine him not thorowly inraged? muſt not a world flow with bloud-ſhed to quench the fury of his iuſt revenge? Surely it would ſo happen were you <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> oh you are but a little <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See what <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great did, when offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous complainers thronged in to plead againſt the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious delinquent; and the whole earth expected <hi>Conſtantine</hi> would revenge the diſreſpect done him, to an everlaſting terrour of al ſuch as caſt ſcoffes and ſcornes: what doth <hi>Conſtantine</hi> that wanted not courage? hee was Great, wanted no power, hee was Emperour of the riſing and ſetting Sunne. Well friends (ſaith <hi>Conſtantine)</hi> you tell mee of a fellow that hath diſgraced mee, and contemptuouſly caſt dirt on mee: hee hath caſt durt upon my Picture, I heare, but nothing doe I feele upon <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> I ſee <hi>Conſtantine</hi> cleane, the glaſſe ſheweth no ordure in my face: your conceit may terme my face fowle and filthily abuſed; but my conceit telleth mee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it, how then can I be angrie? I pray tell me, if <hi>Conſtantine</hi> feele no blow, no wound, no offence, the Picture be torne; yet if <hi>Conſtantines</hi> skinne bee whole, for what ſhall <hi>Conſtantine</hi> be angry?</p>
               <p>So ſhould you diſcourſe with your ſelf, when one reviles you: what are you the worſe? your enemie
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177091:39"/> hewes your name to pieces, teares your credit to tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, hee frets and roares. So as one would thinke he could overturne mountaines of honour into an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſſe of diſgrace, but yet you are never the worſe: he doth but frame your name in his mouth, it is but a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call image of you, it is but your picture, &amp; in the aire, that is ſomething leſſe than a picture in colours. And that name of yours, your picture, hee rowles up and downe his dirtie mouth, and daſheth it with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace: ſay then, your ſelfe are never the worſe, never the fowler, and ſay with <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> why ſhould you be angry? O thrice happy <hi>Conſtantine!</hi> whom hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven favored with that excellent temper, that ſo neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly could breake off occaſions of unkinde quarrels; and not ſpend time in hearkning unto boyes. Play, but better buſie himſelfe in the conqueſt of king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, which made him ſo mighty.</p>
               <p>A great Wit being asked how the Romanes from <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellinum. Ep.</hi> 5.</note> ſo poore beginnings had growne to ſo vaſt an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, <hi>Quomodo Romani ex inopi Rempublicam magnam fecerunt?</hi> Preſently anſwered for them thus; it was becauſe <hi>Acceptâ injuriâ ignoſcere, quàm perſequi male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</hi> The Senat of Rome did not ſpend their time, they waſted not their warlike Legions, they caſt not the coine of the Capitoll, they did neither bruiſe nor buſie that luſtie bodie in revenging privat grudges againſt their neere, and perchance (notwithſtanding one offence or fault) their true-hearted Subiects: but made the beſt of their owne ſtrength about them, to compaſſe victories further from them. Which Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:177091:40"/> when afterwards their children forgot, buſying themſelves in quick exceptions, one againſt another: they ſhaked to pieces their owne mightineſſe, to which otherwiſe al the kingdoms of the world could haue done no hurt, ſaving by adding unto it great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. So doubtleſſe it would be unto you a great happineſſe, if you could reſerve your ſelves for weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier imploiments of profit, and neerer cares: and not go a wrangling for every bable, as children doe for Butter flies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="point">
               <head>Point 3.</head>
               <head type="sub">Antidote 3. <hi>Put off wrongs with ſome pleaſant ieſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOmetimes, it is an excellent piece of wit to cut off quarrels with a ieſt, and not to profeſſe as it were, to be a common crier of ones own ſhame, an aggravater to ones owne diſadvantage. Have not ſo coyiſh a ſtomacke, as to take every courſe morſell like the venome of an Aſpe: looke not ſoure upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very diſtaſte; ſpeake ſometimes merrily when your heart akes, then your ſore will be the leſſer. Ieſts now and then paſſe away evill times, and why not evill tempers? <hi>Rodolphus</hi> the firſt Emperour of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrian <note place="margin">Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us in Flor. Exemp.</note> Familie was ſorely wounded by a careleſſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: therefore his ſubiects in their moſt loving re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects were forward to punish: they had the Archer in hold, and their rigour would faine have beene do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and firſt they will cut off his hands: ſtay ſaith <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphus,</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:177091:40"/> if you had done ſo before hee had ſhot mee, you had done wiſely, but now that I am wounded already, let him goe, and take both his hands with him.</p>
               <p>Thus wiſe <hi>Rodolphus</hi> reflecting, perchance the Archer had noble friends, whom the Emperour was loth to loſe; with a jeſt freed himſelfe from the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of a reſentment, which edgeth on anger, that doth but load a great ſpirit with the charge of a revenge. Worthy <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> who for his integrity was called the <note place="margin">Senec. de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſol. ad Holviam.</note> Iuſt, an inſolent fellow did ſpit in his face, to diſgrace him; yet hee, though chiefe Ruler of <hi>Athens</hi> many yeares, never ſtirred to implore revenge; but ſmiling ſaid: I pray you, my friend, gape not ſo wide, yawne not ſo undecently: though the fellow did diſgorge himſelfe in the chiefe Iuſtice his face, yet <hi>Ariſtides</hi> his thoughts at that time did hang upon more ſerious imployments, and therefore he put off the lack with a jeſt.</p>
               <p>If one grow wilde with you in choler; Laugh, and ſay he acts a mad man prettily, or rather you pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie his frenzie. Will he needs draw your bloud? ſay to him, he is ſicke of the bloudie flux at the wrong end, and wiſh him rather to uſe a Phyſitian, than a weapon.</p>
               <p>Tell him, when he comes to himſelfe, you will come to trie about with him: if he continue ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying words, ſay to your ſelfe, hee doth it but to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe honour; and ſeeing he will buy it of you, hee confeſſeth your ſtore, and his owne want: will you
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:177091:41"/> be angrie with him for honouring you. Hee faine would get honour, and therfore would wound you: and why would you be offended with him, for lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving himſelfe better than you? Though it be not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tie of charitie, yet I would not make it a breach of worldly amitie. Love that liveth with a little, ſhould not dye ſo eaſily.</p>
               <p>Doth ſome pretended friend wiſh you to revenge an old quarrell of one of your Grandſires: tell him you will finde better matter to make expreſſion of your manhood: you will not buſie your ſelfe with braules paſt, nor keep ſo many little bundles of thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny remembrances in your boſom, you have caſt them out quite, to get quiet by forgetting them: Wiſemen have enough to do with things preſent and to come, and will not trifle away time in paſt miſtakings, which cannot be recalled, you would rather goe to burie them: by remembrance, you doe but bring your owne ſhame into new acquaintance, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces, in ſtead of dying, doth raiſe a new encreaſe; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credits, the more you water them with bloud, the longer they wil continue growing. You may beſtow your skill better.</p>
               <p>If a drunken Quarreller open himſelfe to you, and rage; anſwer him, you know you are now at home in jolly mirth and plentie, and that his frownes are but a coppie of his countenance, that you will not dreame you ſtand in a Battalion, where mens hearts muſt lye upon the beſt advantage of their weapon: you will not fal to pell mell amongſt good fellowes:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:177091:41"/> it is pitie the kinde company of <hi>Bacchus</hi> ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay by grievous wounds, let the companies of <hi>Mars</hi> dye of that diet: let that plague fall upon thoſe harſh fellowes, that doe nothing but ſtrike and kill, not upon the merry-hearted cup-man that doth no harme, but fill a Swines belly with droppings of drinke, he doth ſo ſip it: and now and then bite his fellow Hog by the eare, for ſtanding by; for ſtood he not there, they had beene good friends ever. Stout men no more regard cup-quarrels, than wiſe men do little houſes, which children build with ſticks.</p>
               <p>Oftentimes men have no wrongs at all offered them, and yet they will fall into quarrells, and kill one another out of a conceit of wrongs. Such men are much like that tall fellow, who being to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, laid downe his luſtie head on the block, and died with the ſtroake of a pudding: hee certainly beleeved it was a faulchion, and it was a puddings end. Why ſo it is with ſome, that conceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſore trampled with a heavie diſgrace, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to duſt, ſure they thinke it was a thunder-bolt, but there was not as much as a thought: ſay you then ſometimes, that the wrongs offered you are nothing, that they deſerve not to have a puddings end for their God-Father.</p>
               <p>Thus you may jeſt jars out of countenance, and your owne wit in the occaſion may frame you pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier conceits: learne onely this from me, to like this ſleight of ſtepping out of an affronts way. And yet ſometimes you may deſerve good commendations,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:177091:42"/> by laying your ſelfe open unto affronts, and lying under them, by hearing them, and wiſhing they were greater, the more to torture you:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="point">
               <head>Point. 4.</head>
               <head type="sub">Antidote. 4. <hi>Wrongs happening in baſe occaſions, ſuffer them to puniſh your ſelfe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MEn ought to regard as well the credit of good manners, as of good manhood: nay one knowing himſelfe bound to preſerve both, ſhould more readily puniſh his owne perſon, for diſcrediting his behaviour, than puniſh any other for diſgracing his valour. You goe to the Taverne, where wine kindles the veines, and in a jollitie, men are made bone-fires; ſo flaming grow all their faces: by and by happens a Metamorphoſis, all the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie is turned into an herd of Swine, ſome grunt in the corners, others lye in their mire, and nothing but ſtench amongſt them: Doe not you diſgrace your ſelfe mightily by ſitting on this miskin? Why then doe you not thinke of puniſhing your ſelfe, for this foule fact of yours in comming thither, before you puniſh the other fellow for giving you there ill words, or blowes: you will ſtumble at ſtraw, and leap over a blocke. Seeing you have no heart to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtize your ſelfe; let this man whom you terme your Injurer, be your Beadle to whip you: and after you have uſed the rod, you may throw it into the fire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſimirus</hi> King of Poland would needs to dice, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177091:42"/> for want of company fell to it with one <hi>Conarius</hi> a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Martin Cromer de rebus Polon. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 6. <hi>ann.</hi> 1176.</note> meane man: the game was high, and <hi>Conarius</hi> quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly began to below in purſe; his money was gone, and by that time his anger was come: <hi>Conarius</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came furious, and thinking Loſers had leave to ſpeak (ſo it is, when they play with their fellowes) hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got hee played with a King: his money being run out of his reach, his tongue run after it, and played upon the King, and in the end, <hi>Conarius</hi> taking his leave of his coyne, up with his fiſt, and ſaluted the King with a buffet.</p>
               <p>How doth now <hi>Caſimirus?</hi> Doth hee fret at his abuſer? No, with the buffet the King awakes, as it were, out of a dead ſleepe, lookes upon himſelfe, and reflects what he is doing. A King, on whom hangs the eyes, the hearts of a Kingdome, ſporting in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely manner: ſo he abuſeth the hearts of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, for their love muſt follow the King, elſe the heart is out of his place: and who can love diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? Love cannot come herſelfe to what is nought, ſhe may ſend her Hand-maid, Pitie. Well, <hi>Caſimirus</hi> feeles now the ſmart of his owne folly, and thankes <hi>Conarius</hi> for it: you cannot well tell, whether the Kings eare glow more with the buffet, or his face with a reflection of his over ſight: and therefore he never thinketh upon puniſhing <hi>Conarius,</hi> but is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make <hi>Conarius</hi> a pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſher of the King: ſo when his Nobles ſtirred to revenge his wrong; No ſaith <hi>Caſimirus,</hi> not ſo, <hi>Conarius</hi> is my Maſter, hee teacheth me a good leſſon, let him beat me for being
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:177091:43"/> a truant King, and playing at dice with a fellow ſo far my inferiour.</p>
               <p>So if you chance to be carried into an Ale-houſe, and there fixed in the Firmament of good Fellowes: where the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> is browne Ale, that row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all eyes after it: if after a while, like a <hi>Phaeton</hi> or a <hi>Fatuus,</hi> you fall ſtumbling upon one another, and hang like Bees upon each others backs in a bundle: then, if you hap to be abuſed, to be provoked, if one kicke you, and uſe you verie ill, terme him not your injurer, but your benefactor: ſay not he doth you wrong, but that hee doth you great good in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, in making your heart ake, for going to ſo vile a place. Doth one belay you with hard blowes? he doth but ſhake you to awake you, that you may ſee to what place your idle carriage hath brought you: be not therefore angrie with him that ſtrikes you, turne rather your anger upon your ſelfe; buſie it there, and forgive the other which did you no harme, but good ſervice.</p>
               <p>If caſually, you ſtumble upon a crue of merrily diſpoſed lads, and there meet the brave ones, with Tobacco pipes in their mouthes of a yard long, iet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſo ſtout, as if they trailed pikes in an army; that burne their lands at the pipes end, excellent husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not breake up, but burn up houſe and houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping; maintayning that the chimneyes of the forefathers, ought to be turned into the noſes of their children: When you ſee all their noſes there ſo fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that you cannot diſcerne at which end the pipe burneth with the more red-hot fire: if one
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177091:43"/> of this ſparkling company, will bee fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious with you, becauſe you will not drinke: if hee vow, you are no good fellow (as though goodneſſe were not got but by good ale) diſlike the ill ſpeech, but ſuffer it: make it a meanes to loath the place, for the language: be glad you feele there, thornes of ſuch words, that they may pricke you thence. If one call you Coward: beare, and ſay, for beere you want ſtomacke; you have no courage to carouſe: he is the better man at a bottle: wrangle not with him, but chide your ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Doe as the ſtout <hi>Xenophanes</hi> did, when caſually <note place="margin">The French Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy of Pierre de Primandy.</note> being at a feaſt, one upbrayded him, and called him coward, becauſe hee would not play at dice. <hi>Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes</hi> mightily troubled with the abuſive taunt, yet quarrelled not with the fellow, rather anſwered to his tune. I am indeed a coward, fearefull to doe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt things: he would not wrangle for any thing done there, but grew (doubtleſſe) into a great diſlike with the place, where ſuch virulent diſcourſes were uſually uttered. So you, never marke the ſpeaker of an affront, but put a croſſe upon the occaſion, never to come into it againe.</p>
               <p>But oh, ſay you, your occaſion wherein you ſuffer wrongs, is not unworthy: it hath no relation to tobacco, not to <hi>Bacchus</hi> his Alliance; a ſparke of warre, a martiall man, another wiſe well-orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Gentleman, my equall, upon a good cauſe, on a reall ground, with fury provoked me to Duell: and I ſhall dwell in endleſſe diſgrace, if he be not anſwered in the field.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="point">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:177091:44"/>
               <head>Point. 5.</head>
               <head type="sub">Antidote 5. <hi>Beare with your friends: of your foes you take beſt revenge, when you are quiet.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt ſtay: goe not on ſo ſuddenly to overthrow him: remember now, perchance he hath beene unto you a ſtrong friend, and is but newly bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: See firſt if you can recover him, before you caſt him and your ſelfe both away: you would bee loth to loſe a nag, for once ſtumbling; and will you leave a friend, if you finde him once tripping? eſteeme better of old friends than ſo; you may loſe him when you pleaſe, but ſee how you can yet ſave him: true friends be ſcarce found, and in this friend you have had a happy triall of true love: onely this one time, hee hath fayled you, hee hath greatly wronged you, hee hath broken with you fouly; yet let his ancient merits defend this breach: Baſe were the ſouldiers, that upon a firſt breach ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred up their citty; thy friends deſerts are great and worthy, they ſhew themſelves now ſtoutly upon the breach, and day, thou ſhalt not enter as an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to ſubvert them all, Ile not forget them. Thus they parley, it is of the firſt fault, and of a deare friend you will ſay, hee being your friend which abuſed you, therefore you tooke it the worſe; and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will fight to puniſh one that being your friend, would wrong you; were he a foe, you could
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:177091:44"/> better ſuffer him. It is true; <hi>Coſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> the great Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> I beleeve was of your minde, when hee made that madde obſervation upon the Goſpell; you ſhall reade, ſaith he, that we are commanded to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give our enemies: you never reade that we are commanded to forgive our friends; but let a wiſer maſter, feſcue that raw ſcholler that wringeth blood out of the letter ſo quickly: ſhall we, ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> take good at Gods (good friends) <note place="margin">Iob. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 10.</note> hands, and refuſe to take a little evill? Say your friends breath is now an ill blaſt unto you, but hee hath bleſt you with many good turnes; if hee now frowne and looke backe at you, time was, he ſhined on you, to the growing of your beſt fortune; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the merry houres you paſt in his company, and now for his ſake, ſuffer a ſad cloud that will paſſe preſently; <hi>Poſt nubila Phoebus:</hi> ſuffer but a ſhort e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe, <note place="margin">Ovid.</note> and you ſhall clippe and love like good friends againe; after a little cloſe weather, a ſhort ſtorme of hayle, of ſputtering words, the day will breake againe into a hot friendſhip.</p>
               <p>Doth your friend thunder, that one would thinke heaven and earth bee going together by the eares? <hi>Videmus horribiliter vexatum.</hi> Doth the sky <note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſoſt. hom. in Mar.</note> caſt it ſelfe downe in tempeſt? doth your enemy his eye threaten to fall upon you with weapons? Oh ſtand you ſtill: <hi>ſupportamus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Baſill,</hi> to be a friendly <hi>Atlas,</hi> hold him from falling: amidſt <note place="margin">Baſil hom. de ira<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> all the ſhowers in the deluge of anger, be you the dove, hold the branch of Olive in your mouth:
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:177091:45"/> dry you up the Seas of wrath, with your ſilence: So you ſhall begin a new world of happineſſe: for when the paſſion is paſt, <hi>cùm amaritudinem depoſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> when your friend comes againe to himſelfe, <hi>ubi convaluerit,</hi> you ſhall not onely have him thenceforth your faithfull friend, but for ever your humbleſt ſervant; <hi>te ut Dominum venerabitur:</hi> Here is a pretty plot of a victory: you wound your enemy without bloud, you vanquiſh him without ſpeare, and by conqueſt you make him your ſlave, <hi>te ut Dominum venerabitur:</hi> nay, were there mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Gods upon earth; by his voyce, you ſhould come into election, for a Godhead, <hi>venerabitur.</hi> If you tell me, hee which offended you is not your friend, and therefore you owe him no ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as to ſuffer him; nor will you waite the lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his mad fits, or ſtay for his favour, untill the feaver of his furie declines.</p>
               <p>Say then hee be your ancient and bitter enemy: will you goe about to bee deepely revenged on him? yet, your next way is to be quiet, to keepe your ſelfe ſtill: ſay nothing, and you ſhall catch him lying under your feet, heart-broken. Doth he ſwell with fury? looke off him: doth hee runne into your face? let your eare goe by him: doth he roare? hearken to ſomething elſe: doth he mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fret? neglect it: make all, but nothing: that is to breake his very heart-ſtrings, <hi>Si deſpexeris, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crius eum vindicabis.</hi> Deſpiſe him, that is the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elleſt kinde of wrong: for it is all one, as to ſet
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:177091:45"/> one a worke with his fiſts to beate a ſtone wall, wherein he doth but hurt his owne fingers: carry your ſelfe like a wall of braſſe, ſtedfaſt againſt his boyſterous fury, and you ſhall breake the ſtorme only with your ſuffering: <hi>ſine illum fruſtra adlatra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in ſeipſo diſrumpi:</hi> hee will ſwell and puffe ſtill more, finding he cannot ſtirre you: doe you then but ſuffer him, <hi>ſine,</hi> and he with his owne winde will ſwell ſo faſt, that it muſt burſt him, <hi>in ſeipſo diſrumpi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doe you know what you doe when you fret? you comfort your foe; it is <hi>perturbati animi conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio:</hi> that is your raging enemy his delight, to ſee his fury begins to worke upon you, to diſturbe you, to ſhake you, to make you reele, ſo hee will hope to fall you: the faſter you ſtand, the gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier your enemy groweth in rage: whiles you keepe out of his way, hee toyles and runnes the more a madding to ſeeke you: as ſoone as you ſhew your heart diſquieted, with a convulſion of diſcontents, then you ſport and feaſt your enemy: <hi>inimicum plectere,</hi> that is, <hi>iram animumque ſatiare:</hi> Doe you cry out, as if you were ſore beaten, as if you were outed of your quietneſſe and ſafety? that is your enemy his ſatiety: your <hi>plectere</hi> is his <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiare.</hi> Againe ſhew your enemy in his rage, that you are not touched, that hee comes not neere you: and ſo you encreaſe his hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger after you: you make a meere <hi>Tantalus</hi> of Valour, having it onely hanging on his lippes,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177091:46"/> at his tongues end, and is not able to bring it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further; Thus onely with your quietneſſe, you puniſh your enemy, ſo cruelly, that you ſhew a puniſhing power, parallel even to the Poets fiction: you can hurt as much as Poets can faigne.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſtrive to ſtand ſtedfaſt like a rocke, and let your enemy ſtrike, ſee what hee ſhall get by it; <hi>qui laceſsat placidum, magis dolet:</hi> the more <note place="margin">Nazianz: in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione de ira.</note> he rageth, the more he ſuffereth: who runneth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to paſſion with a man that can bide ſtill, doth all one as wraſtle with a tower, which is but to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones armes: or with a phantaſme, whereon you can never catch hold, to eaſe you. Who is wheeled up and downe, deſires to faſten upon ſomething, to hold by: when an arrow com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from a careleſſe Archer, threatned the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of ones perſon; to lay hold, but on the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, to breake it, hath beene an eaſe unto the heart that began to be angred. And ſo you ſee, how by being quiet, you may exceedingly vex ſuch as ſtirre moſt againſt you.</p>
               <p>If you pleade, God hath not made you of ſuch a temper; for ſuch peeces of worke, of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: you are no <hi>Salamandra</hi> in human ſocietie: you cannot live amongſt flames of fury, and your ſelfe not burne: if you come neere furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpoſitions, you muſt grow warme: yet doe thus much; ſcortch not your ſelfe with haſty flames: leiſurely, fire gives unto things beſt ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="point">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:177091:46"/>
               <head>Point. 6.</head>
               <head type="sub">Antidote. 6. <hi>Revenge not your wrongs ſuddenly, leaſt you repent.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DIſcreet <hi>Antenodorus</hi> taught <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pophtheg. Rom</note> that if in anger he were to act any thing, hee ſhould firſt, for his prologue recite an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet, and ſtay ſo much time before he did begin the Tragedie.</p>
               <p>If you be ſo furious, as that your blinde weapon muſt needs bee doing ſomething: yet let a little time firſt paſſe, for Reaſon to riſe and peepe in upon you; <hi>nil facias iratus priuſquam</hi> 24 <hi>literas graecas percurreris,</hi> ſaid <hi>Antenodorus,</hi> ſtay a while. And certainely, a little time will ſtrongly change the liking of actions. This is ſo true, that who beſt governe on earth, oft-times reprieve their owne private reſolutions, till a ſecond meeting; reaſon returnes againe her tale, and then they lead her forth into action with a ſafer liking. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let not Paſſion deny the appeale unto time. When feare tels you, anger ſits on the bench; you are diſcreetly adviſed, from <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to appeale unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and give him time for his aſſociate: and will you goe to duell, will you carry a man to execution in a ſudden fury? who giveth quickely, you ſay giveth twice; and ſo I take it, who is hurt quicklie, hath ever double meaſure. In our ſonnes,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:177091:47"/> the firſt the eldeſt, by inſtinct of nature wee love beſt; but in our thoughts (that be likewiſe ours by a kinde of generation) it is not ſo, there the youngeſt; the laſt fruit, the lateſt, that longeſt hath beene a ripening, is of beſt reliſh, and wholſomeſt, <hi>Poſteriora conſilia ſaniora.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoſius</hi> made a Law, inviolably to be kept tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodoret. in Hiſt. ſua. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</note> his Empire, that ſentence of death delivered in anger, ſhould beare no force, till after thirtie dayes expired: then if after a review by reaſon, when paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion were out of Court, it went currant, it might ſtand: for ſo long time the Emperour would a ſtay, of whatſoever had beene done in anger: if this Law was laudable in actions civill, where reaſon hath roome to look about her: much more it ought to be in actions martiall, where reaſons eyes are quite out: who walketh in the darke, muſt goe by leiſure.</p>
               <p>Therefore doe not ſuddenly yeeld to enter into a quarrell, leſt you repent it; take firſt <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his thirtie dayes leiſure, and forgive for ſo long time: of that that will never repent you: <hi>Neminem peperciſſe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tetrarcha.</note> 
                  <hi>multos vindicaſſe poenituit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tetrarcha:</hi> reſolve well firſt what to doe, elſe you may have more adoe, to undoe it againe, than you are aware of: you may at any time puniſh: It is an eaſie matter to finde a ſtaffe to beat a dog: but if a miſchiefe be once hatcht, it will creepe out of the neſt, and doe you a ſhrewd turne, when you cannot fence it: you may hurt your enemie ſo over-much, that afterwards you muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe your ſelfe to make him amends. That is to doe and undoe.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:177091:47"/>
               <p> Be ſure, not to hearken to your choler, when it firſt breakes forth; whatſoever ſatisfaction it bid you then require, beleeve it not: the firſt anger, <hi>Prima</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Senec. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de ira.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ira,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> doth never guide well, nor will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be well guided, it will not heare reaſon, <hi>Surda eſt &amp; amens,</hi> It is wild and virulent: therefore let it run a while, <hi>Dabimus illi ſpatium:</hi> Let the Whale wallow in the waves, in the deepe of diſcontent, give it lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and cord: and take you ſpace before you ſpeak, before you challenge, before you fight, before you doe any hurt; elſe in ſtead of taking ſatisfaction, you doe vengeance.</p>
               <p>In the eighth of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> the Scribes tell that a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan</hi> 8.</note> married woman was taken napping in another mans boſome: a ſhrewd fault. The husband and his friends muſt needs be revenged: the Chancellours Court ſuddenly cenſured, that with ſtones ſhee ſhould bee ſcratcht to death, for having defiled her marriage bed. Thus in hurly burly they came all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ieſus,</hi> who ſaw them then newly acting mad an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: for it was but <hi>modò apprehendimus,</hi> they were even then newly entred into the action. And <hi>Ieſus</hi> will act unto them the cure: firſt hee goes about to looke a little time; <hi>Ieſus</hi> muſt needs ſtay them, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt <hi>digito ſcribebat in terra,</hi> whileſt he doth write; and what doth <hi>Ieſus</hi> write? no man hath yet told: let me gheſſe, <hi>Ieſus</hi> did write the foure and twentie let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Antenodorus:</hi> I ſay <hi>Ieſus</hi> only aimed to get a little time, for them to think firſt what they were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about, that they ſhould not goe kill a bodie ſo ſuddenly.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:177091:48"/>
               <p> Thus, whileſt <hi>Ieſus</hi> was writing his 24. Letters in that little time, the accuſers perchance reflected, they might have done wiſer not to have made the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo publique; before it was onely the wives hurt, now it became the husbands diſgrace, the childrens infamie. The witneſſes alſo reflected, ſuch as bee ſo buſie to have others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ives puniſhed, ſhould think up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their owne faults, for thereby lawes may bee brought to call upon them with a ſmart reckoning: And ſo with a little pauſe on the matter, but whileſt <hi>Ieſus</hi> writ 24. Letters, the quarrell was quite ended, thoſe that challenged the woman, put up their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons and turned their backes; that when <hi>Ieſus</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ended his <hi>ſcribebat,</hi> lifted up his hand to give order for entring the liſts of Iuſtice, there was no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to go with the woman to the field.</p>
               <p>Are you ſo angry and offended? give me then but a little time, you cannot looſe much by it, you ſhall get to know whether it be fitting what you go about; yeeld me a little ſtay; your delay at leaſt ſhall leave your miſchiefes the fewer: it ſhall ſhew you how to hurt another, with leaſt harme to your ſelfe. And peradventure you may find more: for it is ever true, that <hi>Remedia in remiſſionibus morborum proſunt;</hi> at the <note place="margin">Sen. de ira.</note> declining of the burning ague of anger, Doctor Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doth uſe to preſcribe her Phyſicke. And ſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time you may chance to forget to quarrell by a little delay of quarrelling; ſo it hath happened unto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: when anger is going out, is the beſt time to cure it.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:177091:48"/>
               <p> If no way can helpe you, if nothing can ſtay you, but you will to the field ſuddenly to a Duell; then fare you well, and call upon the gallowes, as you come home: if you be ſo happy, as to live, as to come to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="point">
               <head>Point. 7</head>
               <head type="sub">Antidote. 7. <hi>If nothing can ſerve, there is a tree will ſerve you.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DElictorum impunitas</hi> ſaith the Stoicke, <hi>homines facit audaciores ad malum.</hi> Certainely had Law beene rightly executed againſt Duellers, they had never growne to that head and number as they are now adaies. I aime not to draw Princes to the edge of ſeverity, which ever have in them diſcreet mercy for companion. But thus I preſume to ſpeak; if ever ſeveritie were to walke alone, it ſhould bee to the houſe of the Dueller: for the tender love to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane bloud doth bid you ſpill it, for to ſpare the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpilling of it. Heavens ſtop nothing: let then, when the love of Powers on earth, look about them</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Democritus</hi> maintained, there were two Gods; no more, and cared little for either; <hi>Paena</hi> and <hi>Praemium,</hi> one a Puniſher, and another a Rewarder. And Duel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, I beleeve, do a little <hi>Democratize</hi> from the rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, which inhabites the heavens; the Dueller expecteth no great Preferment, and ſo that God hee little regardeth. As for the other God, the Puniſher,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:177091:49"/> who raigneth upon earth, and men commonly call the King, as ſoone as hee is a little out of the way; the Dueller thinkes he can ſhift, and ſo he cares not what miſchiefes he doth unto mankinde: therefore the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher, God or his rod, ſhould ſtirre abroad ſomthing the oftner.</p>
               <p>If youth were once perſwaded, that whenſoever they make a challenge, their life is ended, their thread is ſpunne, and muſt needs either be cut by the ſword, or crackt on the gallows: their heads muſt off; either by their enemy, or by the hang-man: certainly youth would never enter into Duels. For life is ſweet, and none will caſt away all hopes of keeping it; if one way they hazzard it, yet ſome way they ſtill hope to ſave it. Men ſay, they fight for honour, but who cares for honor after death? not the Dueller. Let him vaunt his fancy, I will but ſmile at it: and thinke even thoſe that you brag have caſt themſelves away for honor, either did it to be rid of loathſom life, or yet hoped to eſcape and live to inioy the glory of their proffer.</p>
               <p>It was wittily diſcourſed by the wiſeſt of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers; the Bull roareth and rageth againſt the Maſtives: ſome hee worieth, others he killeth, and moſt he woundeth: you ſtand by and laugh, becauſe whiles the Bull thus layeth about him, the butcher expecteth, and the combat ended, the Victor Bull is carried away to the ſlaughter. Even ſo, Duellers, they fight, they kill, they keep a roaring like bulls; the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers laugh, and looke about them, and ſoone after the fight ended, the Dueller Victor is to be led by a cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:177091:49"/> to the gallowes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If our times do tell you it is not ſo, then give humble love leave, to drop a teare, and whiſper: young ſpirits may ſport at bull baiting, but greedy gaine ſhould not doe ſo at duelling: let hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane bloud riſe to a dearer eſteeme: let that bloud fall like another <hi>Nilus,</hi> with ſuch noiſe, ſuch cries for vengeance, that thoſe which ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at the bankes of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice (before whom theſe bloudy ſtreams muſt come) be ever deafened unto prices and praiers; elſe time may warrant vices, to ſet fury a worke, a taske for the extirpation of mankind, to rid the earth of men, for a piece of money.</p>
               <p>To talke to you here of things beyond the Moon: of a moſt great God, of a moſt ſtrict Iudge; to come neere you, and ſpeake of a moſt ſevere punishment, an eternall ſmart laied on by a hand ſo heavie, that at one blow, it could ſtrike all the Divels, from the higheſt of the Heavens, to the loweſt Centre of the earth; were to talke to you <hi>Non-ſence:</hi> (therefore here in a corner, I ioyne gallows and goodneſſe together as equally pleaſing you) they may be pretty ſtories to tell women and children; but you will fight with the Divell himſelfe; nay, God doth wiſely to ſtand out of your way, within doores in his heaven, there you meane not trouble him; nor I my ſelf with you any longer, rill you learne more wit.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
